<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The churches hazard deliuered in a sermon in the cathedrall church in Norvvich, vpon the fifth of Nouember. 1629. By Tho. Reeve, Minister of Gods Word at Coleby in Norfolke.</title>
            <author>Reeve, Tho. (Thomas), 1583 or 4-1651.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1632</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 104 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10561</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20832</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118921</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854128</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854128</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19535</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10561)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19535)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1581:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The churches hazard deliuered in a sermon in the cathedrall church in Norvvich, vpon the fifth of Nouember. 1629. By Tho. Reeve, Minister of Gods Word at Coleby in Norfolke.</title>
                  <author>Reeve, Tho. (Thomas), 1583 or 4-1651.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 101, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Augustine Mathevves, for Iohn Grismond, and are to be solde at his shop in Iuy-lane at the signe of the Gunne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1632.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Three sermons; pagination is continuous. Each sermon has separate dated title page. Sermon 2 title page reads: Nabals arraignement: or a Christmasse churle. Sermon 3 title page reads: Moses old square for iudges.</note>
                  <note>Formerly also STC 20833 and 20834.</note>
                  <note>Sermon 2 identified as STC 20834 and sermon 3 identified as STC 20833 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19535:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19535:1"/>
            <p>THE CHVRCHES HAZARD Deliuered in a Sermon in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedrall Church in NORVVICH, vpon the fifth of Nouember. 1629.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> THO. REEVE, <hi>Miniſter of Gods Word at</hi> COLEBY <hi>in</hi> NORFOLKE.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by AVGVSTINE MATHEVVES, for IOHN GRISMOND, and are to be ſolde at his ſhop in <hi>Iuy-lane</hi> at the ſigne of the <hi>Gunne.</hi> 1632.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19535:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19535:2"/>
            <head>TO ALL THE ADHERENTS of the Romiſh Church amongſt vs.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ow commeth it to paſſe, that Rome is become the Seminary of miſchiefe? an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that where Martyrs once abounded, now Conspirators? the faith of that Church being once famous through the world but now her <hi>Bloodſhed;</hi> all Chriſtian Countries ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> her tumults, and many her Treacheries. Can we iudge her that delights in crueltie, the tender <hi>Mother?</hi> no, the<note n="a" place="margin">Rev. 17.4.</note> 
               <hi>ſcarl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t Wh r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>?</hi> Are theſe her gentle warnings? her ſpirituall ſtripes? what to ſtrike Nations to death? Did Chriſt euer preſcribe, that a Church ſhould bee advanced by ſuch direfull deſignes, diſmall ſtratagems? Let his Records bee ſearched, and the Grant of this charter ſhewn. No, this practiſe nature diſclaimes, how much more Scripture deteſts? Traytors are the worſt men in the bad age,<note place="margin">Luke 21. 2 Tim. 3.4.</note> yea the Monſters of the perilous times. Out of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuſcript of <hi>Iudas,</hi> Treaſon may be prooued but out of the Gospel of Chriſt neuer: Oh then that it ſhould b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e held the perfection of Religion, the mould of merit! I wonder thoſe practiſed diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples bluſh not to call themſelues
<hi>Ieſuites,</hi> and that the <hi>Pope</hi> the <hi>Crafts-maſter</hi> of the ſcience doth not hang downe his head in the ſight of the whole world, to ſtile himſelfe the <hi>Vicar of Chriſt.</hi> Oh bleſſed Sauiour, thou which didſt ſuffer thy owne blood to bee ſhed, and hadſt rather looſe thy life then thy meekeneſſe, which neu r ſtruckeſt enemy to death, though thou haddeſt<note n="b" place="margin">Math. 28.</note> all power, which didſt<note n="c" place="margin">Luk 9.55.</note> coole the breaths of them which would haue had fire fetched from heauen, and didſt teach the<note n="d" place="margin">Math. 26 52.</note> Diſcipline of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience to that military Apoſtle which did cut off <hi>Malchus</hi> his eare, which thy ſelfe wert an innoc nt<note n="e" place="margin">1 Pet. 1.10.</note> Lambe, and didſt ſend foorth thy Meſſengers as<note n="f" place="margin">Math. 10 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Lambes, which wouldſt haue king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes
<pb facs="tcp:19535:3"/> ſubdued vnto thee by revealing of myſteries, and not by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priving of life, how wilt thou acknowledge ſuch followers to bee of thy retinue? No here Antichriſt is diſcovered, in that he is ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ppoſite to Chriſt.<note n="g" place="margin">Cum ſitis inhumani, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pij, crudeles, homicidae, non ampl u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itis Ch iſtia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i. <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifer, Carali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Athan l <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p</hi>
65</note> 
               <hi>Seeing y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>are inhumane, impiou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell, homicides, y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e are no longer Chriſtians.</hi> Their ab ſing of the Scriptures, the mingling of their owne works with Chriſts precious ſatisfactions, the ſteame of their Brothell-houſes, their ſhop of Imagery their new built Chaldron of Purgatory, the grounding of the principles of their Religion out of Apocry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phall, allegoricall, parab licall places or out of moſt dark<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and intricate places of Scripture, from which no conuincing argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are to bee fetched, the voluntary confeſſion of their owne Writers that neither<note n="h" place="margin">Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtiation The vtter reiecting of <hi>Hoc eſt c <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pus m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> for a clea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e place, and oncluding <hi>N n poteſt per vllam ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram probati</hi> Fiſher cont. capt. Babilon. n. <hi>8. Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m nes</hi> conf ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing <hi>Sco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us</hi> his opinion (that there is not extant any place ſo expreſſe, that without the Churches d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>claration, can eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently conſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ne vs to admit it) not to be improbable
<hi>de Euch l. 3 c. 23. § Non diſſimili.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e Communion cuſtome. <hi>G e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> de Val de vſu. Euch c. 10.</hi> lade of the peoples deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Communion</hi> in one kind,<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Indulgences.</hi> Roff Aſſert luth conf. art. 18. Cajet opuſc. tom. 1. tract. 15 de Ind cap 1.</note> 
               <hi>Indulgences,</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sacrifice for quicke and dead.</hi> C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſter in co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p. o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th fid. dem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rep 5. c. 2 p 1. 2.</note> 
               <hi>ſacrifice for quicke and dead,</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Prayers vnto Saints and Images</hi> Bat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n in
2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> q 1 art. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.</note> 
               <hi>prayers vnto Saints, worſhipping of Images,</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion into <hi>Limbus Patrum,</hi> no where expreſſed, that Chr ſt w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt thithe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to deliuer the ſoules <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f the Fathers, <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>c <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Can<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> l <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l. c. Theol. c 4</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Chriſts deſcenſion into</hi> Limbus patrum,<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Conf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſion</hi> Gl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſ in G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at. de poen. diſt. 5 c 1 in poenit.</note>
               <hi>Confeſsion,</hi> nor many other points are cleerely to bee proued out of Scripture their revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of the ancient hereſies of the<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Valent ut <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Hera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eonites for extreame v ction.</hi> Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae. l 1 c 11. Aug l <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> hae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> c 16</note> 
               <hi>Valentinians,</hi> and <hi>Hera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleonites,</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Angelic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s for wo ſhipping of Angels,
<hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e haer. c 39.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Angelickes,</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ians for wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhippin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Images. <hi>Epiph haer. 27. Aug. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ar cap 7.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pocrati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns,</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Collyridia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> worſh pping of the vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gin Mary,
<hi>Ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h. haer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Coll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ridians,</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſaeans for reliques,</hi> Epiph <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aer. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3.</note> 
               <hi>Sampſaean,</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ichees for Prieſts ſingle l fe,</hi> Aug Epi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t 74 Id. de mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rib. Ecc &amp; Mani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. l. 2. c. 13.</note>
               <hi>Manichees,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Meſtaleans that Baptiſme doth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> e ſinnes going before, <hi>Theod. diuin. Decr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e de Baptiſmo</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Meſſalians,</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>edales <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oted Franſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canes and Seculars, <hi>Aug de har c 58</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Nodipedal,</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Catha <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for merits, Iſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 1 Etym. lib. 8 c. 4.</note>
               <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thariſts,</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Armezians for wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſh pping of the Croſſe, N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ph l. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. c 45</note> 
               <hi>Armenians,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary poverty, <hi>Epiph haer 61.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Apoſtolickes,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us</hi> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> for hauing blo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the Chalice. <hi>Epiph haer. 34.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Marcus,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Nouatians for doubting of remiſsion of ſinnes, <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b i. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. de Poen. c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. &amp; l. 2. c. 5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Novati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> and others, their Boy-fathers alleadged in ſolemne contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies,
<pb facs="tcp:19535:3"/> the digladiations of their owne Divines againſt them, and the maine points of our profeſſion proved ſubſtantially out of their owne Writers, make m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e to renounce them; but their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies mak m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e to abhorre them, defy them, looke agaſt vpon them; but ſpecially when treaſon comes to be dogmatiſed by their Schoolemen, every Romiſh Theologue almoſt now adayes not being able to compoſe a Body of divinity without this ſangu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inary <hi>Maxime</hi> inſ rted, iuſtifying the lawfulneſſe of Treaſon, and (as if it were a profeſſed
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>) deſcribing; and preſcribing the meanes of it; making no conſcience of it after<note n="d" place="margin">Suarez de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſ. fid Cath. adv Aug. ſect. exc. lib. 6. c 4. n. 18.</note> condemnatory ſentence, yea if the Popes<note n="e" place="margin">Bann 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. p. 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> in erpretatiue ſentence can but bee conceiued it is enough; to doe but deny their Religion, is to<note n="f" place="margin">Sand. de clau. Dan. p 25.</note> runne vpon the ſword of the Church,<note n="g" place="margin">Suarez def. fid. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at adv. Aug. ſect. er. lib. 6 c. 4 n.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8.</note> any perſon then appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Pope m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y take away the life of his Soveraigne, if none bee appointed the Succeſſor may doe it, if there bee no Succeſſor the Kingdome may doe it; yea<note n="h" place="margin">Mariana. inſtit. reg. p <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Mariana</hi> is ſo impud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt that hee ſaith, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at it is a wholeſome meditation for Princes to perſwade themſelues that they may bee then killed, and the party not onely to doe it lawfully but with glory and commendati n. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> I confeſſe was a modeſt Papiſt; his tenets not ſteeped in the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>atiouſneſſe of many; <hi>yet</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Micah
7.4.</note> 
               <hi>the beſt of them is but a brier, and the moſt righteous ſharper then a thorne-hedge,</hi> for when I conſider his<note n="k" place="margin">Bell de pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tif. l 5. c.
6.7.8. Bell de pot. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um. Pont. ad Guliel Barcl. p. 97.</note> treaſonable concluſions, and his damnable Letter to <hi>Blackwell,</hi> what doe I hold him but a Cardinall En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine of ſedition? The Pope is held by many a Holy Father, as if the Sanctuary of peace, truth, and piety were in his breſt, yet when I call to mind how <hi>Vrban<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 2.</hi> held killing of Kings no murther but a zeale to the Catholicke mother, and how many<note n="m" place="margin">Conſider the miſeries of theſe Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours Kings, and Princes. Leo Iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us. Sigon. de rag. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>al. p. 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ovicus pius papi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> maſſ. annal. p. 04. Childe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m in. geſt. Fran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>03. O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ho the gr a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> p. 6. c. 6 Henry the 1. Ben Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d. vit. Hild. p. 2 H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the 4. N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ucl. p 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7. Hen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 5 vr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p p 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2. Lot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ar us Otho Friſ l 7 c 18. Fri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Barba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſſa Nauct p 856. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enry 6 Hoved p 63<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Philip his brother, Nau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. p 898. Otho 4. Wa ſing Yp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſt p. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d. 7. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. col. hiſt. N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ap. p 245. Henry 7. Avent. p 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7. 5 8 W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d. Ni m p <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8. ſo n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Q. o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Naples Nauct. p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>024. Man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed. K. of Nap. &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Nauct. p. 9<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6. C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dinu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Parai. v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ. p 11. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lian &amp; Lawrence the Du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es of Florence, Vol p. 51.</note> Emperours haue beene troubled by Popes with the loſſe of their peace, kingdomes, or liues, and other Kings and Princes
<pb facs="tcp:19535:4"/> in the like manner moleſted, how<note n="n" place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Paris. p. 223.</note> King <hi>Iohn</hi> amongſt our ſelues, and<note n="o" place="margin">Cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g. p. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>Henry</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſecond were put to baſeneſſe, how Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> after the B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll of <hi>Pius Quintus</hi> was never at reſt, how<note n="p" place="margin">Or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Sixt. 5. ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 15<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9</note> 
               <hi>Sixtus</hi> the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t iuſtified by a panegyricall Oration the murhering of <hi>Henry</hi> the third in <hi>France</hi> by a Dominican Friar, I can count the Pope no o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er then a murthering Father, ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Cut throat of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>de, when I recount the maſſacres of <hi>Merindoll</hi> and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Paris,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f that here intende in
<hi>England</hi> at this Gun p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wder Treaſon, I can ſpeake to <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me</hi> in no mil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er termes then God did once to <hi>Niniveh,</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Nah. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 1.</note> Oh thou bloody Citie.</p>
            <p>Oh yee then which are the admirers of that Church, which think it the Paradice where the tree of life doth grow, and hold no ground holy but that which that Church ſanctifies, ſee at laſt the A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mnable impoſtures yee haue b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e miſ-led with renounce that<note n="r" place="margin">Apo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.
1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.5.</note> 
               <hi>Woman of forn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cati ns,</hi> and<note n="ſ" place="margin">2 Theſſ. 2.3.</note>
               <hi>Man of ſinne</hi> bee it for no other reaſon then the e principles of blood; Treaſon can never bee an appendant of the true Faith. And oh yee Prieſts and Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits, the ſpirit of conſpiracy, and nerues of treaſon, who with wit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the whole world, and haue raiſed vp nothing a great while but a learned v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ny, by whom all the Commotions, the turbulencies is the Chriſtian world h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ene either acted, or animated, conſider at laſt what it is y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e practiſe, Treaſon; Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, the attempt of raſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſſe, the v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>red; the ſcandall of humanity, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of Religion; wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> men ſhould not doe it, good men wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not. What therefore will yee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or this ſtill ſtreine your wits, and your neck s? and make your ſelues fearfull to your owne people, odi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>us to vs? no, if reverence to God and man haue not q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ite f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ken you if yee haue not forgotten the honor &amp; ſafety o the men in y ur own corpſes, deſiſt from ſuch hideous, hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible, graceles d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſignes. And the rather becauſe (ſauing the repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of your owne iudgements) yee are circumuented, being but made ſlaues to the ſubtilty, &amp; inſolency of your Pope; for what J beſeech you (by all the pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>les of conſcience that are left in your boſomes) hath beene theſe many yeares the maine incentiue of all your diſloyalties; hath it not beene to make your Pope not onely c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Prieſt but chiefe Potentate in the Chriſtian world? where his temporall iuriſdiction hath not beene acknowledged, there ye
<pb facs="tcp:19535:4"/> haue laboured to thruſt it in by this ſpirituall feat. But (if ye haue but one drop of ſpirituall oyntment left vpon your eyes) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider if the opinion be not as vaine, as the attempt is deſperate; who knowes not the forgery, as well as the ambition of this Title?
<hi>But</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Luke 22.26.</note> 
               <hi>it ſhall not be ſo amongſt you,</hi> damps the <hi>Popes</hi> affected Primacie ouer all Biſhops; but<note n="u" place="margin">Io. 18.36.</note> 
               <hi>my Kingdome is not of this wold,</hi> throttles ouer all his
<hi>Supremacie Kings</hi> &amp; <hi>Emperors;</hi> Chriſt neuer aſſumed it, <hi>Peter</hi> never chalenged it, the auncient Biſhops of the Romiſh Church never pretended title to it, how then ſhould it now come to be a right vnqueſtionable? Search antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties;<note n="*" place="margin">Theo. l. 1. c. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great was ſo farre from ſuffering <hi>Iulius</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> for being his Head that he gaue not, his Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates (but <hi>Euſtathius Patriarke</hi> of <hi>Antioch</hi>) precedency in the Councell of
<hi>Nice.</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Leo ad Cler. &amp; plebem Conſtant. ep. 23.</note>
               <hi>Leo</hi> commanded not <hi>Martian</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour to ſummon a Councell, but made humble requeſt for it by the Clergy and people of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Cum lachry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis &amp; gemiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Leo ep. 14. ad Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſium.</note> and with teares and ſobs he begged of <hi>Theodoſius</hi> to haue had a Councell in <hi>Italy</hi> but could not obtaine it; the words of Pope <hi>Agatho</hi> of old were not imperious to <hi>Heraclius,</hi> and
<hi>Tiberius</hi> the Emperours, but<note n="*" place="margin">Pro obedien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia quam de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buimus. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. Conſtant. Act. 4.</note> 
               <hi>For the obedience wee owe you, Gregory</hi> the Great acknowledged himſelfe the ſeruant of <hi>Mauritius,</hi> for<note n="a" place="margin">Chriſtus do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minari Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratorem militi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſed etiam ſacerdotibus conceſſit. Greg. lib. 2. ep.
103.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt</hi> graunted the Emperour not onely to rule over ſouldiers but Prieſts; in <hi>Iuſtinians</hi> dayes it is euident that the Emperour was held ſo farre ſuperiour to the Pope, that the ſayd Emperor<note n="b" place="margin">Pontifical. Cont. tom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. in vita Vigilii.</note> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed two Popes, <hi>Silverius</hi> and <hi>Vigilius,</hi> and hee himſelfe aſwell as <hi>Theodora</hi> the Empreſſe thanked <hi>Belizarius</hi> their
<hi>Agent</hi> for it; <hi>Eutropius</hi> ſaith, that in former times ſuch wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Popes to Emperors that if the Emperor ſent for the Pope,<note n="c" place="margin">Omni neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecta occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne. Eutropius.</note> all buſineſſe ſet aſide, he went though he knew it were to goe into baniſhment. The boundleſſe power and immoderate Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of Popes ouer Princes in thoſe ages, then were not knowne; are yee not perſwaded in your c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſciences, that the firſt raiſe of Popes, was by the Grace of Princes, and the next by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir owne maſterleſſe Ambition? your owne writers will teſtifie as much. Your Ceremoni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry ſaith that<note n="d" place="margin">Hoc affi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus ante Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolum mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num nem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nem Imperii Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mani coronam ex manu Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificis Romani ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cepiſſe. Cer. lib. 1. ſect. 5. c. 7.</note> before
<hi>Charles</hi> the great, no man euer tooke t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Crowne of the Empire of the Pope,
<hi>Boniface</hi> the eighth, was the firſt that euer inueſted himſelfe in this ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie,
<pb facs="tcp:19535:5"/> and yet (<hi>Major</hi> ſaith)<note n="e" place="margin">Bonifacius 8. multum appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renter defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d Rom. Ponti ex eſt ſupra <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ges in temporali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us quod tamen o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ulatiſſin. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Theologi di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunt eſſe f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum. Io. maior a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſent. diſtinc. 20. q.
2.</note> the Iudicious Diuines of thoſe times held it but a corrupt i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e.<note n="f" place="margin">Mea poteſtas non p nd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t a Papa <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a Deo immedia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, &amp; va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um eſt quod di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i ſolet Papam habere ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Part. vrſp. i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Ludou. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Ludovicus</hi> the fourth, was wont to ſay, that it was a meere vanitie, to hold that the Pope had a Superiour to him vpon earth.<note n="g" place="margin">Poteſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ſae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cu ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> maior eſt ſpi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ituali, nec quod illa e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eſt ſubiecta in aliquo Ioh. de Pariſ. de par. Reg. &amp; papi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. c 5.</note> 
               <hi>Iohannes de Pariſijs</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth abſolutely that the ſecular power is ſupreame.<note n="h" place="margin">Non Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolico iure, N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c enim il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lud tibi da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, quod non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buit, Petrus potuit. Bern. de Conſid. ad Eng. lib. 2. Fides tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum non E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliorum. Hilar.</note>
               <hi>Bernard</hi> himſelfe avoucheth to the Pope, that his power is not by <hi>Apoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call</hi> right Why then fight ye thus for a new inuention? which if it be come to bee a point of faith, yet it is not the faith of the Goſpell, but of the times, and that not of the purer Primitiue times: will yee bee the defenders of an vſurpation? and ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter your liues and ſoules for a fancy of power? Oh that euer men of your acuteneſſe, and acrimony, ſhould be thus infatuated to bee inſtruments of ſuch fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gitous, execrable practiſes for an arrogant perſon? who ſees not that ſince the Pope came to this power, he ha h giuen himſelfe to nothing but to haugten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe, and ſlothful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, he is too great now to open his mouth in a pulpit, or to buſie his penne to diſcuſſe Controuerſies of Diuinity, the zealous and laborious Biſhops of Rome are vaniſhed, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y prea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h only by your lips, and write onely by your hands their chi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> f ſtudy is now to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent miſchiefe, and to in ite you to attempt them; Oh therfore go open your cloſed eyelids, and rubbe vpon your conſciences to take notice of the palbable grafts of the Popes, and to beware th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m; fight not for Tyranny, dye not for Pride, ſhew not leſſe mercy to Chriſtians, then you doe to Iewes and Tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>kes, embrew not your hands in the blood of Princes, with ſhame bluſh ouer that which is paſt, with horror preuent all ſuch future practiſes; get your Pope to giue ſatisfaction to all the World, for all former Treaſons, to burne all ſed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tious bookes, or elſe aſſure your ſelves whatſoeuer ye can colourably pretend to the world<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> an infamy ſticks vpon your Church, and your religion will be held as dangerous as corrupt. Thus out of ardent deſire to procure ſafety to my Country and to get ſuch blacke deformities wiped from the browes of all them that profeſſe Chriſtianitie, doe I offer theſe wholeſome aduertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to your dueſt and deepeſt conſiderations, beſeeching God that your piſtols, poiſons, powders, may now be laid aſide, and that ye may fall to workes anſwerable to true prof ſſion.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours ſo fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ue Chriſtian Reli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>on wil ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ffer. THO: REEVE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19535:5"/>
            <head>THE CHVRCHES HAZARD.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>NEHEM. 4.11.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>And our adverſaries ſaid, they ſhall neither know, nor ſee till wee come into the midſt of them, and ſlay them, and cauſe the worke to ceaſe.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Church is a Particle of Heauen, a quint-eſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce I am ſure from this earth <hi>Hortus incluſus</hi> a Garden en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed,<note place="margin">Cant. 4.12.</note> ſeuered like Paradice from all the world; Gods Suburbs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low; the Royall Citie aboue, the Suburbs below; that <hi>Sedes Beato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi> this <hi>Renatorum;</hi> that the Seate of the Glorified, this of the
<hi>Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Conſtitu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi locum vnum aus condidis v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſum.</note> He which made the whole world, reſerved this one place to himſelfe. Whether God dwell not here, let the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of his Scepter manifeſt; <hi>Iudicia indicia, His iudge
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19535:6"/> menti are teſtimonies.</hi> I can read God preſent amongſt his people aſwell in the patent of his workes, as in the charter of his Scriptures; for<note n="b" place="margin">Pagina au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorem ſuum nunquam ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centes, Amb. ep lib. <hi>10.</hi> ep.
<hi>84.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Theſe are volumes that neuer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale their authour.</hi> How comes it that the Church hath ſtood all this while againſt the formidable rage of the world, but that it is a fenced Citie? It had long ſince beene made a ruinous heape, but that it is the Pallace of the great King.<note n="c" place="margin">Extingere voluit, ſed Deo gratias non valuit. <hi>Bern. ep. 2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The enemy of</hi> Sion <hi>would haue extinguiſhed it,</hi> but God bee praiſed hee could not.<note n="d" place="margin">Ramos con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fregit, radici non nocuit, <hi>Chryſ hom. 10.</hi> de diuite &amp; paupere.</note> 
               <hi>Hee brake of ſome of the branches but hee could not hurt the roote.</hi> From the mouthes of our aduerſaries let vs bee reſolued, whether this be not the <hi>Great Gods Station;</hi> for the deuiſes, deſignes haue beene many miſchieuous againſt it, yea<note n="e" place="margin">Innumerae peſtes Ereb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>infinite Fiends of Hell,</hi> haue beene buſie, boyſterous, for the demoliſhing of it, why preuailed they not? why were they defeated? Oh they fought ſtoutly, but God had the vpper ground of them, their ſwords were too ſhort, and blunt to fight with the <hi>Almighty;</hi> they felt heere
<hi>Digitum,</hi> a Finger more weighty and mighty then mans to oppoſe them; Euery ſuccour then to the Church is a Charactar, and euery deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance an Oracle to euidence Gods preſence amongſt his people. How wonderfully did God here preſerue <hi>Iudah,</hi> when danger was imminent? God I ſay, and not<note n="f" place="margin">Relliquia Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naum, atque immitis Achil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</note> the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques of <hi>Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ylons</hi> oppreſſion, the ſtrength of the captiuity returned; no, God to ſhew the preheminence of his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, the perogatiue of his Church. Let <hi>Iudah</hi> goe on to build the wall, to repaire the breaches of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> their zeale is commendable, their paines acceptable; all awfull and laudable; yea the Deed is Gods, and the Defence ſhall bee Gods; <hi>Iudah</hi> is Gods <hi>Promoter,</hi> and hee will bee her
<hi>Protectour.</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Iupiter al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonans.</note> 
               <hi>That great God,</hi> that can make the battlements of heauen to cracke, and the Axel-tree of the world to fall in pieces with his thunderbolts, takes vpon him the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage of <hi>Iudah.</hi> Let <hi>Sanballat</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">v. 1.2.</note> ſcorn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and <hi>Tobiah</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">v. 3.</note> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ride yea a Senate of wits meet together euen<note n="k" place="margin">v. 7.8.</note>
               <hi>Arabians, Ammonites, Aſbdodites</hi> to conſult, conſpire about a worke of ruth and ruine, yet God will be a tutelar, ſafegarding power.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19535:6"/> For that is the purport of this ſentence, it is rehearſed as a point of bliſſe when <hi>Iudah</hi> lay at the bleeding point, if God had not helped they had beene helpleſſe; helpleſſe? yea liueleſſe, for they had beene ſlaine, and their worke cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed before they had either knowen or ſeene. For our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries ſaid, <hi>They ſhall neither know nor ſee, till wee come into the midſt of them, and ſlay them, and cauſe the worke to ceaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Our,</hi> ſtand here like a people ſeuered from all the <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians,</hi> they peculiar to God and hee to them, for hee is a friend though there bee <hi>Aduerſaries;</hi> hee hath concluded no harme vnto them though they <hi>ſayd it;</hi> hee had eyes ten thouſand times brighter then the Sunne to diſcerne their ſecreteſt practiſes, though they had thought to come vpon them before they ſhould either know or ſee, they ſhall not touch the hemme of Gods garment, nor raſe the skinne of his body, not come to the out-skirts of his people, though they thinke <hi>to come into the midſt of them;</hi> Gods people are ſecured though they coniecture they ſhould bee ſlaughte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>ſlayne;</hi> the conſpiracie ſhall ceaſe, though they ſuppoſe the <hi>worke ſhall ceaſe. For our Aduerſaries, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Our,</hi> ſhew a company, and a company they had need to be, and well knit together, for they are a<note n="l" place="margin">genus inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum.</note> hated ſtocke, they haue
<hi>Aduerſaries;</hi> and no commune Aduerſaries but ſuch as were full-b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt vpon a wretched purpoſe, they had vared as it were vpon it, they had <hi>ſaid;</hi> yea and cloſe dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Aduerſaries, which would come vpon them in no man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſort, giue no warning of their wrath, ſend no open defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of their diſpleaſure, for then <hi>Iudah</hi> might haue brought forth<note n="m" place="margin">pares <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, &amp; pila minantia pili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>col<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urs alike and forces alike, but come vpon them before they ſhall either know, or ſee;</hi> neither will the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe people ſatisfie them, no they would bee for the flower of the garland, for the moſt inſigne, and illuſtrious, for the <hi>Midſt</hi> and not ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o ſhew an angry brow
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ny, or to pa l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y the reaſon o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their diſtaſt, but to make hauocke; to expreſſe their minds at the ſwords point, a ſharpe diſcouery of mens intentions; <hi>confodere, configere</hi> to wound to ſtab, to ſlay; and not onely ſo, but a greater ſpight is yet behind, to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19535:7"/> the meanes of Gods ſeruice, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o get a conqueſt vpon religion, or theſe people are ſtrengthening them<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elues, ſay they in this holy Citie, they are reedifying the wal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> that their God might againe bee worſhipped, well this holy attempt they would hinder; the <hi>Worke</hi> is the eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſore, and the <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rke ſhall ceaſe Our Aduerſaries ſaid, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Text conſider.</p>
            <list>
               <item>A holy Congregation— <hi>Our.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A helliſh oppoſition — <hi>Aduerſaries.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A firme reſolution — <hi>Sayd.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A cunning proiecting — <hi>They ſhall neither know, nor ſee.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A high attempt, — <hi>till wee come into the midſt of them.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A mercileſſe deſigne—<hi>and ſlay them.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A rancour againſt religion— <hi>And cauſe the worke to ceaſe.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Our.</head>
               <p>Firſt, for the <hi>Holy Congregation, Our.</hi> This word be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs not to a ſingle ſoule, but to men vnited, they were ſcattered, but now they are reducted into one; in <hi>Babilon</hi> they lived apart, mourning in their ſecret, ſeuerall corners, to <hi>Iudah,</hi> they are now returned, and there they now ſpeak with a voyce, like the voice of many waters, <hi>Our.</hi> Though before <hi>My aduerſaries</hi> here, <hi>Thine</hi> there, <hi>This mans</hi> in another place, yet now, <hi>Our.</hi> The ſcattered ſtones of <hi>Sion</hi> are gathered together, the Saints are met, there is a <hi>Holy Congregation.</hi>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                  </label> From whence obſerue, that the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches freedome, is a remarkeable, vnſpeakeable bleſſing; that ſhe which remayned ſolitary, is come to her happy ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties:<note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>li</hi> Eccleſ 4.10.</note> 
                  <hi>Woe</hi> to the church when ſhe is alone, <hi>Ioy</hi> to the Church in her troupes, the Church is then clad in her rich attire, yea decked like a Bride in her Nuptiall Ornaments, then the<note n="o" place="margin">Monilia circa collum.</note> jewels are about her necke. The Church in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution is ſayd to be in the<note n="p" place="margin">2. Cant. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>clefts of the rocks, in the ſecret places of the ſtayres,</hi> deſirous to looke ovt, and yet aſhamed to be ſeene, her profeſſion being in oppreſſion, ſhee hides head, and ſhunnes company; not in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> open ſtreets, nor in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19535:7"/> the market place doth ſhe take her turnes, but in the <hi>clefts of the rockes, in the ſecret places of the ſtayres;</hi> not but that ſhee then is, but not conſpicuous; ſhe wants not interna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l entity, but externall felicity: But a Church flouriſhing, is the <hi>Saints</hi> eye-pleaſure, the worlds amazement,<note n="q" place="margin">6. Cant. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>terrible, like an army with Banners.</hi> For an army with
<hi>Banners d ſp ayed, not more goodly to be beheld, then the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>urch with her ranckes filled.</hi>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">Gen. 30.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Give me children, or elſe I dye</hi> ſaith <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> ſo give me my multitudes ſaith the Church, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh; ſhee is then like a<note n="ſ" place="margin">Eſ. 17.6.</note> 
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ine ſhaken with a berry here and there, in the out-moſt boughes.</hi> The luſtre of a Church is gone, when Gods Courts are not filled, and <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> the mother of vs all, ſeemes to be in her Widdow-hood, when many of her children are not at her knees, profeſſing their faith, praiſing their God. See the luctuous, dolorous ſtate of the <hi>Saints,</hi> when the Church is in this diſtreſſeful plight.<note n="t" place="margin">1. Lam. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>The wayes of Sion doe lament, becauſe none come to the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne feaſtes, all her gates are deſolate, her Prieſtes ſigh, her vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins are afflicted, and ſhe in bitterneſſe.</hi> Solemne feaſtes, but no ſolemne appearance, the gates open, but deſolate for want of company; Oh what a brow of anguiſh is there then euery where diſcerned? the Prieſts ſighing, the
<hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins</hi> afflicted, and ſhee in bitterneſſe. But change this ſtate, and what a change of carriage is there then to be ſeene? all glee, and triumph, recreement, and rauiſhment to beh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> d the Church in her excellency, eminency, glory. <hi>David</hi> deſcribing this ſtate, doth it with moſt paſſionate, aff t o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate termes of exultation;<note n="u" place="margin">Pſal. 68.24, 15.</note> 
                  <hi>Jt is well ſeene Oh God, how thou goeſt, how thou my God and King goeſt in the Sanctuary, The ſingers goe before, the Minſtrels follow after, and in the midſt are the damoſels playing with their timbrels.</hi> Then the Church is compaſſed about with her noyſe of muſitians; not waylers, there lamenters, here deplorers in the midſt, but ſingers before, minſtrels following after, and in the midſt damoſels playing with their timbrels. This is <hi>Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary</hi> jubilation, Gods going in Majeſtie vpon earth. <hi>It is well ſeene how thou goeſt, how thou my God and King goeſt in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19535:8"/> the Sanctuary, How!</hi> that is, how Magnifically, like a Prince in Triſne. There is not a more delectable ſpectacle vpon earth, then the face of a Church viſible; then the Church,<note n="*" place="margin">Pacem prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fert Iren.</note> 
                  <hi>Carrys a torch before her,</hi> not creepes vp and downe in the darke, but carrieth torch-light in her hand; yea, though be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for no man knew where ſhe was, but held her for loſt, yet then they come foorth, and out of joy of heart, and jucun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity of ſpirit, point at her, as at the Moone in the firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.<note n="x" place="margin">Ecce Luna ecce vbi eſt. Aug tract. in <hi>1</hi> ep Ioan.</note> 
                  <hi>Behold the Moone, Behold where ſhee is;</hi> the eclipſe is gone, the wayne is paſt, <hi>Behold the Moone, Behold where ſhee is.</hi> The Church with her Congregations about her, make Gods family to be in it's ſplendor, then<note n="y" place="margin">Apparet Deus &amp; l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>qui turcum ſanctis Amb. lib. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi> de Iacob.</note> 
                  <hi>God yeelds an appearance of himſelfe, and vouchſafes to haue familiar parley with his Saints.</hi> O joyous thing to haue but a ſight as it were of Gods bright brow in his houſe, and to heare but the ſound of his lippes going in his family, where there is an vnity, as they termed it of collection, not a Logicall, but a kind of tranſcendentall Vnity, an Vnitie no other then an Vniuerſalitie, <hi>Our.</hi>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> This ſerues to reproue them which doe ſo little rejoyce in the happy eſtate of the Church, or if rejoyce, I am ſure are not tranſported. The Church is viſible, but not their ſpirituall delight, and comfort for the ſame viſible; their hearts ſpring not, their tongues chaunt not. God had ferventer affections in the time of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches triall, then in the time of the Churches triumph. Our forefathers then wiſhed for <hi>Sions</hi> proſperity, with groanes in their breſts, teares in their eyes; they wiſht for it, and<note n="z" place="margin">Exe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tatus dies omnium v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>is venit Cyp. lib de lapſis.</note> 
                  <hi>The day longed for of all is come;</hi> We their children enjoy it, enjoy it, but ioy not in it, bleſſe not G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d for the happy fruition of it. Our religion is not in bondage, but whether the gratitude of moſt be not, I leaue it to judgement. God hath vnlockt his gates vnto vs, ſet open his Courts, but we come not into his gates with thankeſgiuing, nor into his Courts with praiſe. I ſee many profeſſors, but few con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, that confeſſe the pretiouſneſſe of Gods favours vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs. Are theſe the flouriſhing times of Religion? it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares not by our devotion. Where are they that are as if
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19535:8"/> they dreamed, in a holy traunce, to ſee our Captiuity retur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned like the Rivers in the South; to behold the bliſſe of the times? no we ſee the <hi>Spouſe with her threeſcore Queenes, and foureſcore Concubines, and the damoſels without number a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout her,</hi> but we do not count her <hi>Bleſſed.</hi> Oh how deſerue they to have perſecution againe that know not what it is to have freedome, and to have the Altars of God broken downe amongſt them, that doe not bind the ſacrifices with corde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o the hornes of the Altar. Oh therefore<note n="a" place="margin">Vbi benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium ibi ſit of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficium. Amb.</note> where the happy bleſſing is manifeſt, there let the dutifull accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of it be apparent; Let your eyes bee dazeled with the bright beames of the light of the Goſpel, and your eares glow with the ſweete charmes of ſaluation. If it be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable to you to enter into Gods <hi>Tabernacles;</hi> into Gods <hi>Tabernacles</hi> aboue your ſeeled parlours, into Gods <hi>Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles,</hi> aboue the palaces of Princes, then cry out<note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>4.1.</note> 
                  <hi>O how a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miable are thy Tabernacles thou Lord of hoſts!</hi> Know the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betweene <hi>Babilons</hi> thraldome, and <hi>Judahs</hi> liberty, ye have not now ſingle ſoules, or a few priuate perſons, but a <hi>Congregation;</hi> Yea,<note n="c" place="margin">Ad eſt mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum cohors candida. Cyp. de lapſis.</note> 
                  <hi>There is a white band of Chriſtian Souldiers</hi> to magnifie God, to maintaine profeſſion. We are in our multitudes, <hi>Ovr.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Adverſaries.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                  </label> Now let vs come to the <hi>Helliſh oppoſition, Adverſaries,</hi>
                  <hi>Ovr,</hi> had a companie, and <hi>Adverſaries</hi> hath a company; company againſt company. From whence obſerve, that the Church muſt reſolve vpon <hi>Oppoſites.</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Io. 15.19.</note> 
                  <hi>The world loues her owne,</hi> and God forbid we ſhould be her <hi>Owne</hi> to be loued of her; no,<note n="e" place="margin">Nigros cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodit lividu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> vngues Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial.</note> 
                  <hi>The envious bites his blacke nayles againſt vs,</hi> we may ſee his malice at his fingers ends.<note n="f" place="margin">Inter Babi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonem, &amp; Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem nulla pax ſed guerra continua. Ber ſer <hi>2.</hi> de pugn. ſpirit.</note> 
                  <hi>Betweene Babilon and Ieruſalem there is no peace, but continuall variance,</hi> Yea,<note n="g" place="margin">Quanta ab exteris paſſa eſt Id ſer. <hi>29.</hi> in Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>How many things does the Church ſuffer of them that are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out? They are without,</hi> and ſo in battell array againſt them that are within they are <hi>Without,</hi> and ſo let them which are within ſtand vpon their guard. How ſhould the Church be Militant, if ſhe had no ſtandards ſet vp againſt her? The devill would ceaſe to be an enemie if he ſhould raiſe vp no
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19535:9"/> oppugners; when can the ſeede of the woman bee in a ſure league with the ſeede of the Serpent? when can Chriſt bee dearely affected of <hi>Antichriſt?</hi> no he is<note n="h" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Againſt,</hi> his malice is written in his browes, tooke for no benevolent affections from him. Superſtition is the profeſſed oppoſite of truth, whoſoeuer carrieth in his mouth the name of a falſe God, proclaimes deadly feaud to all Gods true followers, as <hi>Luci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> told <hi>Vrbicius</hi> for condemning of good
<hi>Ptolomeus,</hi>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">Quod Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians nomine gaudet &amp; gloriatur ad puntendum commotus es. Niceph. Call Ecc. hiſt. lib. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>33.</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</note>
                  <hi>Becauſe he reioyceth, and glorieth in the name of a Chriſtian, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fore thou ſetteſt thy ſelfe to puniſh him.</hi> Wee muſt expect no ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere affection from infidels, or
<hi>Misbeleeuers,</hi> no they are <hi>Ban-dogges</hi> to the Church; no friends to God, and ſo our <hi>Adverſaries.</hi> This ſerues to ſtirre vs vp to heedineſſe;
<hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries</hi> they are, and oh that we ſhould count them <hi>friends!</hi> Will the Lambe ſit downe, to reſt quietly, when the Wolfs jawes are open? Will the <hi>Keepers</hi> of the Vineyard be reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe in their charges, when the Foxes are round about the hedge? Haue they once maliced vs, and will they be no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger miſchieuous? Yes,<note n="k" place="margin">Serò recuſat iugum ferre quod ſubij<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Sen.</note> 
                  <hi>hardly can any man deſiſt from thoſe courſes he hath beene inured to.</hi> Wee haue beene once in perill by theſe <hi>Aduerſaries,</hi> then how ought wee ſtill to be in dread? They are ſtill
<hi>Aduerſaries,</hi> and ſo ſtill infeſters, moleſters; the flame may bee put out, but the aymers are ſtill remaining; though like the vncleane ſpirit in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, they haue beene once diſpoſſeſſed, yet if they ſhould find the roome ſwept and garniſhed for them, they would returne with ſeuen ſpirits worſe then themſelues; ſhall wee not thinke them fully to be <hi>Aduerſaries,</hi> till we haue taſted of r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ine by them? If we ſhould dreame of tranquillity, I am ſure there is no ſecurity, they that haue once bent their ſwords againſt our throats, we ſhould doe ill to ſleepe qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly by their ſides.<note n="l" place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ug 16.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>p Sampſon, the Philiſtines are vpon thee.</hi> 
                  <hi rend="sup">m</hi> 
                  <hi>Let vs be prepared for buffets and blowes.</hi> Looke in envies jaw-bones, and ſee if there be any white teeth in her mouth, ſtand at the threſhold of malice, and liſten if there bee any parley of peace in the houſe; no as the Prieſt tolde <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lba,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="sup">n</hi> Looke to thy ſelfe for the <hi>Blood-ſuckers</hi> are not
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19535:9"/> farre. Our <hi>Adverſaries</hi> pretences may be faire, but their purpoſes are diſmall; their blandiſhments may bee ſweete, but let not too much affiance be put in them.<note n="o" place="margin">Sint e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iae. ne ſint <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>xu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viae.</note> Let not our eye-browes be cloſed, for feare the skinne be pluckt ouer our eares; their nayles may bee payred, but they will grow againe; for rancorous, ſpleenatiue they are, full of amaru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency, malevolency, heart-brent, hand-bent, no State-<hi>Ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi> no Church-advancers, no God helpe <hi>Adverſaries, Our,</hi> and <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r Adverſaries.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Sayd:</head>
               <p>Now let vs come to the firme reſolution, <hi>Sayd;</hi> And if about a good buſineſſe, well ſayd, but be the buſineſſe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo bad, yet not toung-tied in it, though it were a thing not fit to be thought, yet ſayd. <hi>Aduerſaries,</hi> and ſo ſpight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,
<hi>Sayd,</hi> and ſo wilfull, for that is the meaning of the word, they were inflexibly, irrevocably bent vpon it.<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                  </label> From hence obſerue the raſh reſoluteneſſe of vngodly men, euen to the moſt damned practiſes, they haue ſold themſelues to commit euill, as it was ſayd of <hi>Ahab,</hi>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">Hoſ.
9.9.</note> they are <hi>deepely ſet.</hi> Puſillanimity they hold a baſe defect, but baſeneſſe they hold no exceſſe, there is in them a fiduciary fortitude (as the Moraliſts terme it) to things vnſeemely. Is it courage to attempt evill? yet<note n="q" place="margin">Pſal. 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.5.</note> 
                  <hi>they encourage themſelues in an euill purpoſe;</hi> for be the action neuer ſo evill, yet they are as full of animoſity about it, as if it were about the ſaving the liues of their parents<note n="r" place="margin">Sueton <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Caligula</hi> was wont to commend one word <hi>Vnmooueableneſſe,</hi> that were the action neuer ſo odious, cruell, yet he would neuer change colour nor countenance at it, ſo theſe are daunted, deterred at nothing; they ſay vpon that, that all the world ſhall ſay againſt the horribleneſſe of which fact, ſhall make the eares of all to tingle, and the eyes of Infidels to gaze; they ſay, that is gage themſelues to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlines, as if all the powers of heauen ſhould not be able to croſſe them, they are<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Ariſtot.</note> firmed in their opinions; they fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and looke that others might be confirmed.<note n="t" place="margin">Prou. 27.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Iron ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth Iron,</hi> that their confederates might not ſtart backe,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19535:10"/> they bind them to it by a ſolemne couenant of their lippes, it is
<hi>ſayd,</hi> and ſo not afterwards to be gain-ſaid, no man muſt ſpeake againſt it, deſiſt from it, for his promiſe is out to the contrary; that it might be ſetled, it is ſayd, <hi>Our aduerſaries ſayd.</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> This ſerues to exhort all perſons to carry in their boſomes mollified hearts, and tender conſcienc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s to quake at ſinne; for if mens hearts come to be ſtupified, and their conſciences cheualriſed, what villany are they not fit for? whileſt<note n="u" place="margin">C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bet vires ingeniumque pudor.
<hi>Ouid.</hi>
                  </note> ſhamefaſtneſſe remaines in man, it reſtraynes both power and wit in euill things; but if the cheekes haue once loſt modeſty, and the conſcience remorſe, the blacke face, and deformed viſage of the moſt nefarious, horrid intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will not terrifie them, no not ſo much as make them bluſh; be it a piacle, and moſt execrable offence, yet they retract not from it, but devou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r themſelues vnto it, <hi>Say, Our Aduerſaries ſayd.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                  </label> Now let vs come to the cunning projecting, <hi>They ſhall neither know nor ſee.</hi> From hence obſerue, that there is no miſchiefe like to the ſecret.<note n="*" place="margin">Gravis eſt illis fortuna quibus eſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentina: <hi>the Poſie of</hi> Germanicus.</note> Thoſe accidents are <hi>grieuous which are ſudden,</hi> vnexpected, vnſuſpected dangers, how dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult are they to be auoyded? a cloſe villany is an ambuſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, a latitant foe, a pitfall, the hand of miſchiefe hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the blow before it was knowne to be lift vp, the ſnare is on the heele before it was diſcerned to be layd, the poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is in the throate before it bee ſeene what manner of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor it be, yet theſe are the priuy practiſes of the wicked, their attemps clandeſtine, they ſerue vnder the <hi>Prince of darkeneſſe,</hi> and therefore they loue to doe all in darkeneſſe: knowledge they thinke would make their actions abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid, and therefore their actions are couert;<note n="x" place="margin">Cum vincere apertè, Non datur, inſidias armaque tecta parant. Calamitatis abſtruſa illece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breſa fallacia. <hi>Cyp lib. 1. ep 2.</hi>
                  </note> when they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not openly deſtroy, they prepare <hi>treacheries and engines of craft,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="sup">y</hi> there is a flattering face of a hidden calamity. A thiefe they ſay comes of a word that ſignifieth<note n="z" place="margin">Fur <hi>of</hi> Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vus.</note> darke, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he takes the opportunity of darkeneſſe, to accompliſh his ends, ſo theſe by ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iue, ſurr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itions courſes, put in practiſe their deſignes. <hi>Dalilah</hi> will ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e off <hi>Sampſons</hi> ſeuen locks, before ſhe tell him of any Philiſtins, ſo theſe take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all ſtrength before the forehead of an aduerſary be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19535:10"/> looke for no <hi>Worthies</hi> here, for they ſhun light, nor for any ſignall of battell to be giuen, for they truſt more to their projects then their proweſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,<note n="a" place="margin">Pſ 11 2.</note> 
                  <hi>They would ſhoot ſecretly at the vpright in heart,</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Pſa. 10.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>They lurke like Lyons in their dens.</hi> So that <hi>Archers,</hi> and <hi>Lyons</hi> they are; <hi>Archers,</hi> but no noone-day, but mid-night <hi>Archers,</hi> or <hi>Archers</hi> that would ſhoot in a cloud; and
<hi>Lyons</hi> they are, but lurking ones, not roaring in the fields, but watching in their dens.
<hi>Cain</hi> doth not challenge the field of <hi>Abel,</hi> no<note n="c" place="margin">Gen 4
8.</note> walke into the field with <hi>Abel,</hi> like a brother, not like a butcher, yea,
<hi>Abels</hi> blood is ſhed, before <hi>Cains</hi> malice ſeene. <hi>Ioab</hi> embraced
<hi>Amaſa;</hi> though embruing be his purpoſe, yet embracing is his practiſe; he embraces till <hi>Amaſa</hi> fals dead out of his armes; he cries not <hi>Eſtne pug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na?</hi> come ſhal we try our valour? but<note n="d" place="margin">2. Sam. 20.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Eſtne pax?</hi> Is it
<hi>Peace?</hi> and thus with a ſword hid in the ſcabberd of peace, doth he ſtrike him into the fift rib that he died; is this captaine-like? no caitiffe-like. Go fetch the child that I may<note n="e" place="margin">Mat. 2.8,</note> 
                  <hi>Worſhip</hi> him, ſaith <hi>Herod. Herod</hi> it ſeemes would become very deuout, but let not the Wiſemen truſt him, for then he will make them looſe the title of <hi>Wiſemen,</hi> yea, make <hi>Babes</hi> of the <hi>Wiſemen,</hi> for <hi>Herods purpoſe</hi> is not<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Non ſeruire ſed ſaeuire,</hi> Raulins, ſer 3. in Innocent.</note> 
                  <hi>to Worſhip,</hi> but to worry. And thus the Churches <hi>Aduerſaries</hi> loue to doe all in obſcurity, their chiefe prop is ſubtilty;<note n="g" place="margin">Egregiam vero laudem, &amp;c.</note> Noble praiſe, high honour, no doubt: All men may ſee they are giuen to jgnominious courſes, which would do ſuch things, as till they be effected, men ſhould neither know nor ſee; they are all for ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals, to take men on the ſuddaine, that men might be wrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked before warned, and they might be felt as <hi>Aduerſaries</hi> before they be either <hi>knowne, or ſeene.</hi> From hence I might caſt ſhame vpon the faces of our <hi>Aduerſaries,</hi> for how may all the world take notice of them to be but baſe-ſpirit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, whoſe chiefe engine is craft? it ſeemes they are aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of their God, which cannot be helped but by ſuch pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie practiſes. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> But vpon this I will not ſtand, onely from hence let me exhort you all to cleaue cloſe to God, for if he watch not for vs, wee are like to fall into ſudden dangers from ſuch ſubtill enemies. Oh that the perils of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19535:11"/> ſhould be ſo many, and the prouocations of the Nation ſo rife, that wee ſeeke not by reuerence, and obedience, to keepe Gods eye vpon vs, to ſearch out the purpoſes, and to diſcerne the practiſes of the wicked againſt vs.<note n="h" place="margin">Heb. 4
13.</note> All things are naked before him, but many things are hid from vs. Therefore ſeeing wee cannot watch ſufficiently for our ſelues, let vs get God to keepe vigils for vs; wee had neede to keepe him ſure, or elſe we are not ſure of ſafety. Our Aduerſaries haue ſecret projects in hand, not bruited in our ſtreets, nor hung vp vpon our City gates, but privily contriued, they would be vpon vs before wee ſhould ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>know or ſee. Our Aduerſaries ſayd, they ſhall neither know nor ſee.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Till we come into the midſt of them.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                  </label> Now let vs come to the high attempt: They are for the <hi>Midſt. Till wee come into the Midſt of them.</hi> From hence obſerue that the ambition of the Aduerſaries is at the <hi>Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,</hi> that not a few poore abiects might endure the ſmart of their power but the chiefeſt liuers, that as<note n="i" place="margin">Sueton.</note> 
                  <hi>Caligula</hi> would haue men ſo to be ſlaine that they might know them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to dye, ſo theſe would bee Authors of ſuch a miſery, as it might be felt to be a miſery, they would be in the midſt to bee in the midſt of miſchiefe,<note n="k" place="margin">Vniuerſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> praem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nult vt non pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tus, n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orum la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tera, ſed faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>em ocul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ue gla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iis, ac tell<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> impeterent. <hi>In his Pharſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lian warre againſt</hi> Pompey, <hi>Plut.</hi>
                  </note> that as <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded his ſouldiers to fight at the eyes of his enemies, ſo theſe would fight at the
<hi>Eyes</hi> of the Countrie, that theſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtrooke out, the reſt of the body might not know how to guide it ſelfe; the cropping of ordinary hearbes in the Garden will not ſerue their turnes, no they are for ſtriking off the heads of the talleſt poppies in the Garden, as<note n="l" place="margin">Plut.</note> 
                  <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinius</hi> the proud was; Let <hi>Nehemiah</hi> heere and his chiefe followers bee laid hand on, and the ſpirits of the reſt will ſoone faile; command the <hi>Midſt,</hi> and <hi>Maſter</hi> of all. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> This ſerues to exhort Great men to bee great Promoters of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, not to excell more in the fame of their deſcents, then in the feruour of their deuotions; not only to looke to be great Wonders in their Countrey, but great Beauties to the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19535:11"/> Church. For <hi>Rich</hi> men, <hi>Neuters?</hi> Great men,
<hi>Atheiſts?</hi> Am I in the boſomes of none? The Country complaines her ancient Gentry is decayed, the Church complaines her religious Gentry is decayed; their Fore-fathers bowed their knees to God, and they to their Paramours; that means which the one ſpent in almſdeeds, and the maintenance of the Goſpell, the other ſpend in pride, and riot. Are there none that in ſteed of being <hi>Great Ornaments</hi> to their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey are <hi>Great Botches,</hi> or <hi>Great Burth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ns</hi> to their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey? their Greatneſſe ſeruing them to no other end, but ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to bee a ſhelter for licentiouſneſſe, or a club to daſh out the braines of pouerty with? Some there are I know, that ſtand vpon their true termes of honour; that as their
<hi>Chriſtian</hi> names are ſet before their ſir-names, ſo they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre piety before gentry: And oh let all be thus addicted, and that euen for the very perill greatneſſe ſtand in. For <hi>Aduerſaries</hi> there are, and at wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m are their aimes? the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fimates? no, the Potentates; the loftier the pedigree, the greater foment of their malice; at their high blood, are their high aims; whatſoeuer theſe ſimple ſoules may endure, yet the <hi>gentle ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rk</hi> is he whom they would quench,<note n="m" place="margin">Cui ger<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>a proauis ingena.</note> which hath the race of famous <hi>Beau-pieres</hi> to illuſter his ſtocke. The <hi>Aduerſaries</hi> loue to ruffle the purples, to giue a Rent in ſcarlet, to twitch at the golden chaines, to enter in at the painted portals. Greatneſſe is their eye-marke, they would bee in the <hi>Midſt. Our Aduerſaries ſaid, they ſhall neither know, nor ſee till wee come into the Midſt of them.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>And ſlay them.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                  </label> Now let vs come to the mercileſſe deſigne, <hi>And ſlay them.</hi> From whence obſerue that nothing, but <hi>Bloodſhed</hi> can true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſatisfie the
<hi>Aduerſaries</hi> of the Church; they come not to make ſport, but ſpoyle, not to fray, but to <hi>Slay;</hi> not to marke out enemies, but to maſſacre them; not to plead the right of a quarrell, but to ſubdue, ſubuert; they bring<note n="n" place="margin">Iacula mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifera,
<hi>Pſ. 7.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Weapons of death</hi> along with them, they are men throughly armed. Did yee neuer ſee the mouth of enuy open? Heare what dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19535:12"/> menaces ſhe ſends forth;<note n="o" place="margin">Diglutiamus eos, <hi>pſ
124.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Let vs ſwallow them vp quick;</hi>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">Diſperdamus eos de gente, <hi>Pſ 83.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Let vs ſcatter them from being a Nation,</hi>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">Exinanite, exinanite, <hi>Pſ.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Downe with them, Downe with them euen to the ground.</hi> Haue not the <hi>Aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> thinke yee, wide throats that can ſwallow vp men quicke? Doe they not carry a whirle wind in their lips, that can <hi>ſcatter men from being a Nation?</hi> are they not perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Artiſans, yea ſome of Sathans diſmantlers (who is called the<note n="r" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Rev 9.11.</note>
                  <hi>Deſtroyer)</hi> that neuer ceaſe till they come to the ground-worke? yet this is the mercileſſe rage of the Churches Aduerſaries, <hi>Deſolation, Deſtruction</hi> is that they aime <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>; their ſwords they thinke neuer ſhine bright, till they g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>r with the blood of the Saints; they are not worthy they ſuppoſe to bee counted <hi>Aduerſaries,</hi> vnleſſe they can ſacrifice to their <hi>Dagon</hi> a fat burnt offering of Profeſſors corpſes. Howling is their melody, firing of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, breaking of Scepters, caſting downe Thrones, dying the ſtones of the ſtreets in crimſon is their pleaſurable ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; that as
<hi>Sylla</hi> filled a po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le of blood, and then ſet his hands by his ſides,<note place="margin">Ob quam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Plut.</hi>
                  </note> and cryed out, <hi>Oh what a noble act haue I done;</hi> and as <hi>Claudiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> killed men only that hee might ſee how fine a thing it was for men<note n="t" place="margin">Vt exper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>um fac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deret. <hi>Suet.</hi>
                  </note> to breath out the laſt gaſpe; So theſe exerciſe all ſort of barbarous ſauageneſſe, and count it but their recreation the perfection of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; they meditate vpon <hi>Slaying.</hi>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> This ſerues to ſhew vs what kindneſſe wee are to expect from our
<hi>Aduerſaries,</hi> what but bloodſhed? I know not whether thy life bee deere vnto thee, but ſure I am this is that they deerely thirſt for.<note n="u" place="margin">Netu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> feri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate Lyc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on.</note> The enemy of profeſſion is knowen well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough in his cruelty.
<hi>Chriſtendome</hi> hath his dolefull pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures hanging vp in euery corner. There are ſome happily that care not if the <hi>Aduerſaries</hi> were now in the <hi>Midſt</hi> of vs, for begin they not to palliate their dealings, to collaud their courſes? yea euen to cenſure them, that thinke hardly of them? Oh what are ſuch but Sicophants, aſſentatory ſpirits? they extoll Crocodiles, magnifie Vipers;<note n="*" place="margin">Deus dicit Homicida eſt, &amp; tu ad illum tanquam ad medicum cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris? <hi>Chry. orat. 5. in Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daeos.</hi>
                  </note> Does God tell vs they are murtherers, and ſhall we hold them as Phiſitians? hath God marked them out as
<hi>Aduerſaries,</hi> and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19535:12"/> ſhall wee eſteeme them men of mercy? no I ſay God keepe vs out of their furies, or els ſure I am we haue ſeene our beſt dayes, ſo ſoon as they preuaile our Kingdome euen giues vp the Ghoſt; a truculent, ſanguinary people are they, giuen to ſlaughter; as heere, <hi>Our Aduerſaries ſaid, they ſhall neither know nor ſee, till wee come into the Midſt of them, and ſlay them.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>And cauſe the Worke to ceaſe.</head>
               <p>Now let vs come to the rancour againſt Religion. <hi>And cauſe the Worke to ceaſe.</hi> As if they ſhould ſay this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie they count the holy Citie, this they are now fortifying that they might ſacrifice, worſhip; well this we will hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, this fruſtrate, <hi>And cauſe the Worke to ceaſe.</hi>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                  </label> From whence obſerue, that the free exerciſe of Religion is anex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruciation, a prime grieuance to the <hi>Aduerſaries.</hi> For let that bee ſuppreſſed, and then they are quiet, but let that haue any liberty, and then their hearts gnaw them, their galls flow ouer, and they are ready to fall out into any out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages;<note n="x" place="margin">Mat. 10 22.</note> 
                  <hi>Yee ſhall bee hated of all men for my names ſake.</hi>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> cauſa omnis o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit &amp; perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis.
<hi>Muſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Chriſt alone is the cauſe of all hatred, and perſecution.</hi> As they are men they can bee at peace with them, but as they are Chriſtians they deteſt them. <hi>Caius Sceius</hi> (ſaid the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens once) <hi>is a good man, euill onely becauſe a Chriſtian:</hi> So that if men weare the open cogniſance of
<hi>Chriſtianity,</hi>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">Bon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s vir C. Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us malus tantum quod Chriſtianus, <hi>Tertul. Apol. adv. Gent.</hi>
                  </note> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> there bee a cleere brow of profeſſion ſeene, it is enough to ſet all the world in a tumult againſt them; as ſore eyes can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not endure the brightneſſe of the Sunne, ſo ſuperſtiti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not endure the light of the truth. If the <hi>Woman</hi> be clothed with the <hi>Sunne,</hi> and haue the
<hi>Moone</hi> vnder her feet,<note n="a" place="margin">Rev 12.1.</note> and a crowne of twelue ſtars vpon her head, let her looke to her ſelfe, it will not be long before the great red
<hi>Dragon</hi> will lift vp his ſeuen heads, and ten hornes, and perſecute her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the wilderneſſe,<note n="b" place="margin">Plin.</note> as the noyſe of timbrels make Tigers run mad, ſo the melodious ſound of profeſſion make the maligners of the Church to rage; they cannot ceaſe, till the <hi>work ceaſe.</hi> This teaches vs how highly we ought to eſteem
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19535:13"/> of religion;<note place="margin">Non eſt res parua quam ſic infectantur hoſtes. <hi>Bern. ſer. 31.</hi>
                  </note> that is moſt pretious that is moſt maliced, <hi rend="sup">c</hi>
                  <hi>It cannot bee no ſmall matter, that the enemies are ſo offended with.</hi> Our aduerſaries ſpleene may teach vs the excellency of our Religion; they moſt enuy it, therefore wee ought moſt to prize it; Religion aboue birth, aboue goods, aboue life. Oh that thou ſhouldſt valew any thing, and vilifie Religion! no,<note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 6.11.</note>
                  <hi>Where the treaſure is, there let the heart bee alſo:</hi> bee not reckleſſe, or remiſſe wherby the deuotions of it be ſlac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, or the purity of it corrupted; contemne all things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout thee, rather then Religion. That ought moſt to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce thee, becauſe it moſt teenes the <hi>Aduerſaries;</hi> it is the grand incentiue of their diſtaſt, the vpſhot of their malice; the hindring of the <hi>Worke</hi> they aime at more, then at the
<hi>ſlaughter</hi> of the perſons. <hi>For our Aduerſaries ſaid, they ſhall neither know, nor ſee, till wee come into the midſt of them, and ſlay them, and cauſe the Worke to ceaſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus haue I told you a ſtory out of <hi>Iudah,</hi> and is it not the vine Image of our owne Country? were they in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and were not wee at an exigent? What was this but the moſt fatall, exitiall day that euer was appointed for our Nation? It ſhould haue beene <hi>Englands</hi> autumne, <hi>Romes</hi> ſpringtide; <hi>Englands</hi> Veſpers, <hi>Romes</hi> Mattens;
<hi>Englands</hi> Exequies, <hi>Romes</hi> Feſtiuall: They began to cry out with them in the Tragedy,<note n="e" place="margin">Thebis laeta dies adeſt, Ara<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> tangite ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, pingues ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ite victimas. <hi>Senec.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Rome</hi> thy joyfull day is at hand, once let vs ſing <hi>high Maſſe,</hi> and make a fat ſacrifice of the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants.</hi> They had a long time curſed vs at <hi>Rome,</hi> and they ſaw wee waxed neuer the leaner; they told the world in their Councels, and Controuerſies that we were <hi>Heretickes,</hi> and they ſaw their word would not be taken, for we ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Chriſtendome the true <hi>Heretick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> in the
<hi>Conclave;</hi> theſe courſes they ſaw would take no place, therefore they would fall to other practiſes; the penne they ſaw could doe no good, therefore they would try what policy could doe; ay,<note n="f" place="margin">Hoc, hoc mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtro noſter v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tur dolor.
<hi>Senec.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>This, this is the onely medicine for our grieued minds.</hi> Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy is the Popes onely weapon, treaſon the laſt refuge of <hi>Rome:</hi> They had often tryed what their Gun-pouder would doe aboue ground, and they euer found it flaſhed backe in

<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19535:13"/> their faces; the bliſters were ſtill to bee ſeene in <hi>Spaines</hi> cheekes, therefore they will try what their <hi>Gun-powder</hi> will doe vnder ground; their Saint
<hi>Peter</hi> falls to <hi>Salt-peeter,</hi> a <hi>Cracke</hi> with that they thinke ſhould make the heart ſtrings of the <hi>Land</hi> to breake, and of the world to tremble; they had ſpent ſo much Gun-powder vpon vs before that their <hi>Indies</hi> were almoſt waſted, well they will now be at leſſe charge, 36 barrels ſhall worke the feate; what, <hi>England</hi> that was held before even impregnable, now to be conquered with 36 barrels of <hi>Gunpowder?</hi> Yes, if a place convenient can be but found out; and may wee not let theſe men alone to chuſe their advantages? Well, what ſhall the project be, to winne <hi>Dover</hi> Caſtle? no, that had too tough walls for ſuch ſcant proviſion; what then, to be Maſters of the To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer? no, there were too many roaring Watchmen vpon the walls to drive them from that attempt; what then, to deſtroy the Vniverſities? no, that they knew would have ſtood them in ſmall ſtead, learning now ſo abounding, that they ſhould have found an <hi>Vniverſity</hi> all over the Kingdom; what then, to blow vp Tiburne? that indeede they ſpigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted much, becauſe it had quartered many of their Traytors; yet they conſidered, that that pluckt downe, there was more
<hi>Timber</hi> to have been gotten in <hi>England;</hi> what then, to batter downe the Princes Pallace? that indeede had beene ſomething, yet there they ſhould have wanted ſome of their
<hi>Adverſaries:</hi> the project therefore in concluſion was for the Parliament; if wee know not where the ſtrength of our Land lay, our <hi>Adverſaries</hi> can ſhew vs; where but in the Parliament? and not in this openly to aſſault, but ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly to blow vp; a Parliament was gathered together, and <hi>Rome</hi> would have diſmiſſed it with a ſtratagem; an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt manner of breaking vp, they would have diſſolved it with Gunpowder; broken vp, blowne vp;
<hi>England</hi> gave the ſummons, and <hi>Rome</hi> would have given the writ of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture. Could this plot have beene ſo layd, that it might have come from above, a man would have thought it had beene <hi>Heavens-blow,</hi> the ſtroke of <hi>God;</hi> but the Papiſts have
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19535:14"/> no power above, all their ſtrength lies beneath, it had come but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rom H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll, it had beene but the ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y of the <hi>Devill.</hi> The <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſay they would faine bring vs to Heaven, but then the force of their courteſie lies in pulling of vs vp thither with Gunpowder; as for all their E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gines of Doctrines, they doe but puſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>owne, ſtrike to hell. I have read that in <hi>Rome</hi> there was once <hi>via ſacra</hi> a Holy way, ſhall I thinke that ſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l remaining? no, I rather beleeve there is <hi>Via ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinea,</hi> a bloody way. They ſay their Images have ſweat blood, and that they have found blood in the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> let them talke of thoſe miracles as long as they will, ſo long as they worke not this miracle to make a Kingdome ſweat blood. But this they would doe, yea this they had done, if God had not wrought a Miracle, to make Tiburne ſweat blood in ſtead of the Parliament; wee lay at the point of death, and the Papiſts were comming with this plot as <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame vnction</hi> to ſend vs out of the world with; For, for the State to have received the ſtab, and Religion the ſtifle, was as this day determined, decreed. <hi>Our Adverſaries had ſaid they ſhall neither know nor ſee till we come into the midſt of them, and ſlay them, and cauſe the worke to ceaſe.</hi> Give me leave to runne ſhort deſcant vpon my Text, and to fit every parcell according to the preſent occaſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Our.</head>
               <p>Were wee not at this time gathered together into com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies? was there not the face of a
<hi>Holy Congregation, a Church</hi> viſible amongſt vs? Ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Babylons</hi> yoake not long before had beene vpon our neckes, ſince the dayes of Queene <hi>Mary</hi> the graſſe was ſcarce growne, where their flames had beene; they needed then no barrels of <hi>Gun-powder,</hi> their pitch-barrels and faggots ſerved the turne; yet I ſay at this time our captivity was ended, and our <hi>Church</hi> come to a moſt fulged eſtate; for by the comming of that famous
<hi>Queene Elizabeth</hi> to her <hi>Throne; Elizabeth indeede, the oath of God,</hi> or the
<hi>fulneſſe of God,</hi> ſworne to his cauſe, repleniſhed with his heavenly endowments; ſhee,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19535:14"/> who was as a poliſhed corner in <hi>Gods Temple,</hi> as a golden pot of
<hi>Mannah in his Sanctuary,</hi> the <hi>Orient pearle</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> world, yea the <hi>Bright ſtarre</hi> of the <hi>Earth</hi> in her dayes. <hi>Oh</hi> whom ſhould I recount thee to be,<note place="margin">Oh quam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> memorem<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> as incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, as invincible; not greater in the conqueſt of her ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, then the peereleſneſſe of her vertues; the <hi>Queene</hi> of <hi>England</hi> by her title, of the world by her deſert;<note n="g" place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dead yet ſpeaketh;</hi> who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e memory is written in the hearts of her ſubjects, the beſt Chronicle; a virgin, and yet the Gandame of Honour; a Woman, and yet a<note n="h" place="margin">Terror Achivis.</note> 
                  <hi>Terrour of Ter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>magaunts;</hi> which paid h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r ſoul <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rs with the gold of <hi>India,</hi> and m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de <hi>Cadiz</hi> the tiring roome of her Captaines; which turned an invincible <hi>Armado</hi> into a Sea-bonfire, and made 88 like a <hi>Clim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ct ricall</hi> yeare to the ſtate of Spaine; which in her dayes for her Princely deportment, ſeemed the Maſter <hi>peece</hi> of Royall perfections, and for her manifold preſervations, the <hi>Miracle</hi> of <hi>Gods</hi> providence; whoſe governm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt was throughout glorious, not like the Reignes o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſome Princes that wee read of in other Hiſtories, whoſe governments h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ved to their ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>jects, like the ſeaſons of the yeare, a cheerefull ſpring at firſt, comfor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>able Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer afterwards, but at laſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>full <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ll, and a nip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping Winter; or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">Dan. 3.</note> N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>buc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dnezz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s Image, the hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of gold, the breaſt of ſilv r, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rds nothing but braſſe, iron, and c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay; as
<hi>Ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o</hi> wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<note n="k" place="margin">Ad quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que nu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m. <hi>Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>five yeares</hi> was n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table in his government and <hi>Caligula</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f whom <hi>Suetonius</hi> thus r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>port,<note n="l" place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nus qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſi de Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipe, reliqua vt de m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ro n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Hitherto haue written as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f a Prince, but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards I muſt write as of a M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſter;</hi> But as for her, the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fell out of her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> with honour, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> laſt yeares be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as famous as h r firſt, her people bleſſing their ſelv s that they dyed before
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cauſe the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> a Prince behind them, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it was ſaid of the Subiects in the dayes of
<hi>Auguſtine;</hi> wh ch lived with more M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtie, and dyed with more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> then any of her Predec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſ u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s in a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yeares before h r; which deſerved a tombe of gold at her death, as <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d; and to haue had Statues ſet vpon her honour in every houſe, as <hi>Marcus
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19535:15"/> Aurelius</hi> had after his departure; whoſe Sepulcher, (and ah that I ſhould ſpeake off her Sepulcher) is the monument of euerlaſting renowne, more to bee regarded with all due reſpect, then any of the Paynims vrnes, or the Popiſh ſhrines; whoſe name is the joy of our hearts, the Triumph of our tongues; which can ſcarſe to this day bee pronounced without panting breſts, and dropping eyes; whoſe body is gone to ſleepe in a bed of ſafe repoſe, whoſe ſoule is in the Chauntry of Heauen, for<note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gaudet v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuſ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ue Angel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> tantum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> tangere.</hi> Chry. hom 15. de diuit. &amp; pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere.</note> 
                  <hi>Euery one of the Angels deſired to catch, to carry ſuch a burthen to God.</hi> Shee I ſay, for <hi>Faemineo generi tribuuntur.</hi> All theſe bleſſings of the Church are to bee attributed to her, as the happy reſtorer of them; <hi>Illa Eccleſiae ſcintilla,</hi> ſhee, the bright Sparke of the Church warmed vs, when wee were almoſt frozen to death in that brumall ſeaſon of Popery, and like a good Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nched our dropping veines, when they were almoſt l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ft empty of blood; ſhee brake the yoke of <hi>Egyptian</hi> bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, led us through the red Sea of prepared dangers, ſeated vs in the land of promiſe, fed us with the honey and milke of Evangelicall truth, brought home the Arke of God with Triumph, and ſet our Church like a Citie upon a hill; as <hi>Ani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>laſinutha,</hi> that renowned Queene, who followed <hi>Theodoricus</hi> that veſſell of blood,<note n="n" place="margin">Vas ſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis decreta mala emenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit. <hi>Platina</hi>
                  </note> mended all the cruell de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees; So this renowned Princeſſe remoued all the ſharpe ſtatutes, and the ſhadow of her Throne proued a ſhadow of refreſhing to the Profeſſours of Religion.<note n="o" place="margin">Iudg. 5.7.</note>
                  <hi>Surrexi ego Deborah, Surrexi ego mater in Iſraele;</hi> I <hi>Deborah</hi> aroſe, I aroſe a mother in <hi>Iſrael.</hi> A ſtep-mother wee ſeemed to haue before, a naturall mother now; fourtie fower yeares nour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing up her ſubjects with the breſts of ſincere profeſſion: And her ſucceſſour prouing a ſucceſſour of her faith, as well as her Throne: King
<hi>Iames</hi> memorable for his wiſedome, and graces, confirmed this happineſſe vnto vs; in ſo much that Paradice ſeemed not fuller of pleaſant fruits, then wee of faithfull Proteſtants: not a ſcattered flock were we at this time, but a fold well filled, wee were in our multitudes. <hi>Our</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:19535:15"/>
               <head>Aduerſaries.</head>
               <p>Next Aduerſaries. And who are Aduerſaries to vs, if not <hi>Romes</hi> ſqui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t-eyed brood; they are Papiſts, wee Proteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, and as the ſaying was of old,<note n="p" place="margin">expectas vt Quintilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ametur.</note> Doſt looke that <hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilian</hi> ſhould be loued? <hi>Quintilian</hi> that was the Oratour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the vices of the times; ſo doſt looke that any Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant, that hath laid open the nakedneſſe of the whore of
<hi>Babylon</hi> ſhould be tendered by her Followers? no as <hi>Fabri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> enuied all that
<hi>Marcus Aurelius</hi> did: ſo we muſt looke for nothing but the ſpirit of contradiction, and contention in all our paſſages.<note n="q" place="margin">Ganius Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus quod os ſuum obtura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verat Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtomus, coepit tyrannidem exercere. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſm in vita Chryſ.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Ganius</hi> the <hi>Arrian</hi> becauſe S. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi> had ſtopped his mouth, burſt out into tyranny: So becauſe we haue gagged the obſtreperous throate of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts, that they cannot ſo rifly, or ſuccesfully belch out their Doctrine of Deuils amongſt vs, they ſwell with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice againſt vs; yea they haue ſacrificed in hatred againſt our cauſe, as it is reported of <hi>Caligula,</hi> that he ſacrificed to Enuy: Marke
<hi>Rome,</hi> and ſee if it be an auſpicious planet to our Church, no it lookes with malignant aſpects; I will looke for honey in the neſts of Dragons, as ſoone as for affection in the followers of <hi>Antichriſt;</hi> their Vatican is the Councell-chamber of miſchiefe to vs, the Popes keyes are but picklockes to our ſtate; It was neuer well with Chriſtian ſtates, ſince Popes came to weare Triple Crownes; what hath hee to doe with Crownes?<note n="r" place="margin">Plat.</note> the <hi>Phrygian</hi> Miter that <hi>Sylueſter</hi> 1. wore vpon the cold Mountaine of <hi>Soracte,</hi> would become him well enough; when Popes come to weare Triple Crownes, then oh yee Chriſtian Princes your Crownes ſhake on your heads; but why a Triple Crowne? a Triple jeſt; that his Followers might thinke they could want no meanes vnder ſuch a Diadem'd head? or wherefore elſe? where is hee King? of <hi>Paſquius poſte,</hi> the Lady
<hi>Ioanes porphiry</hi> Chayre? and the Curtiſans ſtewes, where like a Prince hee takes tribute?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Conſtantines</hi> donation pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to be ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous.</note> I know no other Kingdomes he hath, vnleſſe I would credit ſome Ieſuits, who ſay hee is King of Heauen, Earth, and Purgatory; as
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19535:16"/> for Heauen indeed (though <hi>Rome</hi> boaſt of many miracles) yet I neuer read, nor heard, that God ſent him downe a Crowne from heauen; for Earth ſtrange it is that Chriſt (whoſe Vicar the Pope pretends to be) neuer woare crowne but that which was put vpon him in ſcorne, a Crowne of Thornes, and yet that the Pope muſt haue his browes fille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: as for Purgatory indeed, that is a <hi>Newfoundland,</hi> and if the world were well rid of Popes, it were no matter if there hee woare a Crowne. But in the meane time till this doubt bee reſolued, by what right the Pope c mes by his Triple Crowne, I am ſure of the ruth that hath follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vpon it: triple woe is threatned to all them, that will not yeeld obedience to the T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iple Crowne: wee like not of his pride, then the proud man waxes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uiſh, and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>trical to all them that will not approue of him: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is the<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                     <hi>Genius Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>i,</hi> Calv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n. ad Regem Ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ae.</note> Fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ury to haunt the Goſpel; the Proteſtants Little-eaſe: I know not whether all amongſt vs will count theſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Aduerſaries,</hi> but ſure I am that they are they that once chayned vs vp in the botome of their l thſome priſons, and burnt our bodies t aſhes, they left vs no other viſibility of our Church but Martyrdome, nor no other monuments of our Religion, but ſuch as were fetched from their flaming ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kes, they ſuppreſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d our writings, depriued vs of our liues, and ſuffer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d none but their owne ſworne Scribes to bee pen-men of h ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ries, and then, askt vs where was our Church before Luther: Are th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe friends courteſies? I know not, let brainſicke lymphaticke, bewitched, beſotted perſons led away with an aſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ntatory, or an abderitious ſpirit conceit them to bee Friends, but ſure I am when time was they were ſuch deere Friends as made vſe of their time, and vſe of our blood: therefore for my part I ſee the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies eye in their heads, the gall of Aſpes in their boſomes, <hi>Aduerſaries</hi> they are:
<hi>Our,</hi> and <hi>Our Aduerſaries.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Sayd.</head>
               <p>Next, <hi>Sayd.</hi> And oh that it ſhould be ſayd, that <hi>Rome</hi> ſhould not
<hi>ſay,</hi> to any thing! what the intrepid men of the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19535:16"/> earth, and not hardy to any enterpriſe? They ſcotch at a miſchiefe? and be faint-hearted in any peſtilent pernitious deuiſe? Let them ſerue no longer vnder
<hi>Antichriſt,</hi> who is ſayd, to be<note n="t" place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>deus facie</hi> Dan. 7 20.</note> a man of an impudent countenance, as if he could bluſh for nothing; their Maſter can infuſe courage into them, they ſhall merit by it; and when he that ſits in the chayre, will thus authoriſe, countenance ſinne, and lay down hire aforehand, euen to put them into his <hi>Rubricke,</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord them in his Kalender for Saints (the higheſt prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment theſe men looke for) what villany will not our <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries</hi> undertake.<note n="u" place="margin">Plutarch.</note> 
                  <hi>Scipio</hi> ſayd, that if he bade his ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers throw downe themſelues from the toppe of a rocke, they would not refuſe it: So theſe men will throw downe themſelues into the bottome of hell at the <hi>Popes</hi> command. Here was an action odious, horrible enough, yet was it not <hi>Sayd?</hi> Yes, they had bound themſelues vnto it by oath; and taken Sacrament vpon it; <hi>Romes</hi> oathes! <hi>Romes</hi> Sacraments! oathes, the ſpring-heads of conſpiracy; Sacraments, the broad ſeales of treaſon: Now then beeing thus mortiſed in miſchiefe, what can ye looke for, but pertinacy in the worke. <hi>Excordes?</hi> no, <hi>Effrontes;</hi> heartleſſe? no browleſſe in it; fervid and vigorous, that it might have beene diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched, two yeeres ſpace could not rebate their edge, nor make their hearts relent from this horrid enterpriſe, with joynt conſent, and vnchangeable purpoſe, doe they ſettle themſelues to it: when <hi>Faux</hi> was apprehended, and examined, whether it touched not his conſcience to bee the Actor of ſuch a wretched intendment, hee anſwered like a man ſteeped in <hi>Roomes Lees,</hi> that it repented him of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but that it was not executed; ſo that this was not ſome floating conceit, or ſwimmering reſolution, but as ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly concluded and obſtinately vowed vnto, as euer was any thing; it was decreed, it was <hi>Sayd, Our Aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries ſayd.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>They ſhall neither know nor ſee.</head>
               <p>Next, <hi>They ſhall neither know nor ſee.</hi> This is the point of cunning, and doubt not of that to be there, when
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19535:17"/> 
                  <hi>Rome</hi> is the <hi>Schoole-miſtriſſe</hi> of ſubtilty, the very
<hi>Accademy</hi> of helliſh pollicy; where Ieſuits are lutors, the Pupils can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but bee ſubdolous; If ye would have a ſnare to bee layd, ſend for theſe crafts-maſters; they are the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cunning Artizans of the world, verſed, exerciſed in all ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſute, fraudulent courſes. Would ye haue a taſte of their ſubtilty? there needes no more to reliſh your palates, then the remembrance of this dayes intention. I haue read of many craftie plots, as of<note n="u" place="margin">Gen. 34.</note> 
                  <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Leui,</hi> that ſet vpon the
<hi>Sichemites,</hi> whilſt they were ſore of their circumciſing, of<note n="x" place="margin">2 Kings 19</note> 
                  <hi>Adramalech,</hi> and <hi>Sharezer</hi> that ſlew
<hi>Senacherib</hi> when he was worſhipping in the Temple of <hi>Niſroch,</hi> of<note n="y" place="margin">Knolles.</note> 
                  <hi>Chaſis Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beg,</hi> who ſ ying vnto <hi>Hadrianople,</hi> like a diſcontented fugitiue and hauing gotten ſome authority in the Citie, on the ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine ſet vpon the warders at the gates, and having ſlaine them, let in his ambuſhment not farre off, and ſo betrayed it into the hands of the <hi>Turkes,</hi> of<note n="z" place="margin">Knolles.</note>
                  <hi>Terhates Baſſa,</hi> who feyning himſelfe to be at the point of death, ſent for
<hi>Ales-Beg,</hi> and his foure ſonnes, with pretence, that if he ſhould die, he would commend his gouernement into his hands, till <hi>Solyman</hi> his Maſter ſhould otherwiſe diſpoſe of it, and ſo with this wily deviſe, hauing drawne them to him pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently put them all to death, of<note n="a" place="margin">The watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>word beeing Nir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, in which were thirty thouſand ſlain at Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople. Procop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et Euagr.</note> thoſe deſperate wretches in the dayes of
<hi>Iuſtinian,</hi> that went with ſharpe weapons ſecretly vnder their garments, and ſtabbed men to death, no men knew which way. But of all ſubtill deuiſes, this carries the ſuperiority. For conſider the paſſages in it: To the Prieſt it is diſcloſed vnder ſeale of confuſſion, ſo that he muſt not r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ueale it. Next, the Actors had ſworne, that neither directly, nor indirectly, by word, nor circumſtance they would diſcouer it, ſo that they had made ſure worke at home, Confeſſors, and complices are bound to ſecrecy, like
<hi>Angerona</hi> the goddeſſe of ſilence, that the Poets ſpeake of, which holdes her finger vpon her lippes, with a tablet vpon her breaſt, and this inſcription vpon it, <hi>Heare, ſee, and ſay nothing, Papirius</hi> was not more ready to cut his tongue out of his mouth, becauſe he ſhould haue beene forced to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19535:17"/> confeſſe his treaſon, then theſe would haue beene ready to haue beene diſcerpted, eviſcerated, to haue had limbe torne from limbe, rather then they would haue had any thing brought to light. Conſider further.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, the place wher they wrought vnder the ground. They are not for a roome, where the light of the ſun (that bright and broad eye of the World) could haue diſcerned them nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther where men with their two ſparkling planets in their heads, could ordinarily view them; no, they lurk in their the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſh corners, they are for a caue, a dungeo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a vault, a cloſe cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler: who could there haue ſpied out any thing, but he that needed neither eye to ſearch, or to haue window to be ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, or vault doore to be vnlocked, to whom darkenes and light were both alike? but for men they were ſure enough.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The time when they wrought, in the night; Night is that which wicked men take vp for a miſt to their actions, a mantle to their wretchedneſſe.<note n="b" place="margin">Nocte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>atent mendae vitto<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ignoſcitur om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni. <hi>Ovid.</hi>
                  </note> Faults haue then gotten their couerts, and men may ſinne by a kind of priuiledge. This was the opportunitie they tooke, when honeſt men were at their reſt, then they were watching, and ſweating, to conuey in their engines of horror.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The materialls whereupon they wrought, which were chiefely gun-powder.<note n="c" place="margin">Contra terra motum nulla latebra, nulla fuga. <hi>Petr. 91. Dial.</hi>
                  </note> Againſt an earth-quake (ſaith <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarch</hi>) there is no hiding, nor ſhifting; ſo ſay I for Gun-powder. The blaſt is inevitable, for all them within the compaſſe, it is a quicke diſpatcher; In a plague, a man may eſcape, in a battell a man may come foorth aliue, againſt poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, a man may haue Antidotes, but from Gun-powder what muniment, or preſeruatiue? no, it is the ſtrongeſt arrow in deaths quiuer.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The colour they ſet vpon the worke, it was to lay in winter proviſion. Were not theſe men (thinke you) much to bee commended that could prouide ſo well againſt a hard Winter? and was not that Maſter thinke you very happy that had ſuch a faithfull ſeruant as
<hi>Faux,</hi> to lay vp in ſtore for him? but the Maſter ſhould neuer haue made vſe of this prouiſion for himſelfe, neuer haue warmed himſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:19535:18"/> with the billet, nor haue had ſo much as a draught out of the 36. barrels, the Maſter herein me thinkes was a ſtrange kind of prodigall; oh but it was for friends, it was for a Parliamentary breakfaſt, and Papiſts care not to beſtow much vpon ſuch a courteſie for vs; there were Lawes to be made, and they would haue them to be proclaimed, <hi>Cum ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitu,</hi> with noiſe: indeed it had beene the lowdeſt trumpet that euer the earth heard, or ſhall heare, except the trumpet vpon moun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Sinah,</hi> and the laſt trumpe; Heere are Popiſh proc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>amations of Lawes,<note n="d" place="margin">Mugitu la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nta <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>li, om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lerent
<hi>Greg. Naz in Mon.</hi>
                  </note> they would fill all the sky with a lamentable roaring.</p>
               <p>Well, the deviſe was ſo great, that they began to ſend forth their Propheſies t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their friends, <hi>That the memory of novelties ſhould periſh with a cracke, and in a moment ſhould their bones be cruſhed;</hi> yea, they thought a man might have ſeene any thing in the Aegyptian darkneſſe, as ſoone as have had any thing in this enterpriſe diſcovered; in ſo much that when it was revealed, <hi>Faux</hi> (that <hi>Cerberi Faux,</hi> if it may be lawfull to vſe the word, that jawe of <hi>Cerberus</hi>) vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered this blaſphemous cenſure, that not God but the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill</hi> had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>icovered it. Now lay all theſe things together, and conſider with your ſelves whether mans eare ever heard, or mans heart can conceive a more ſecret plot; no, our <hi>Adverſaries</hi> were cloſe enough, like <hi>Baſilisks,</hi> they would have kill'd before they had beene ſeene. <hi>Our Adverſaries ſaid, they ſhall neither know, nor ſee.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Till we come into the midſt of them.</head>
               <p>Next, <hi>Till we come into the midſt of them.</hi> And were not our <hi>Adverſaries</hi> aymes as haughty? were they not for the <hi>Midſt?</hi> the height of authority? the heart of command? Yes, <hi>Rome</hi> would be felt in her ſtroke. They care not for ſome eminent man, or ſome chiefe familie, but for the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; a Nationall Stratagem,<note n="e" place="margin">Ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> our Ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ome muſt haue pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed from her higheſt toppe. Twelue men were ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut to br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng into bondage, a whole Kingdome with one ſtroke, yea, with one blow to make a g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nerall thrall; the <hi>Papiſts</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:19535:18"/> ſtrike home. They would put out all the lights of the Land at a blaſt, what a darke houſe had there beene? <hi>Rome</hi> hath a ſtrange kind of extinguiſher. They would batter downe all the bulwarkes of the Kingdome at one Cannon-ſhot: <hi>Mahomet</hi> the Great, <hi>Solyman</hi> the Magnificent, nor any of the mighty martiall ſpirits in the World, euer had ſuch ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillery. The King in his Throne ſhould haue bene blowne vp, the Queene his conſort in wedlocke, ſhou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d haue beene his conſort in woe, the Prince at their knees, ſhould haue beene heyre apparant to nothing but their miſery, not a Noble-man ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uld haue beene left, not a Prelate to gouerne the Church, not a Iudge to defend the Lawes, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> many in hundred o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Knights, and Burgeſſes, ſhould haue be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e fetcht away with the jmpetuous guſt of that whirle-wind. How neere ſoever the <hi>Papiſts</hi> might have beene vnto vs at other times, I thinke theſe had beene in our boſomes, <hi>In the Midſt. Our Aduerſaries ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yd, they ſhall neither know nor ſee, till we come into the midſt of them.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>And ſlay them.</head>
               <p>Next, <hi>And ſlay them.</hi> And what but <hi>Slaughter</hi> can be expected from
<hi>Rome,</hi> when the bloody bourr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſſes of the World, have there their ſetled manſions? For there to kill men, to deſtroy ſtates,<note n="f" place="margin">Peritia eſt, ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> eſt, vſus eſt. <hi>Cyp ep 2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>it is a skill, an art, a cuſtome.</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Tanquaem Leonin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciem Romani Imperis. <hi>Plut.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milcar</hi> ſayd, he bred vp his foure ſonnes, like <hi>Lyons whelpes,</hi> to the deſtruction of the Romane Empire: So theſe like the wilde beaſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s breed, are br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d vp to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>are in pieces the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of Chriſtian ſtates.<note n="h" place="margin">Orcus vo is ducit pedes.
<hi>Sueton.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Hell rule ouer you,</hi> was it ſayd in the dayes of <hi>Nero.</hi> So hell is not greedier to devoure ſoules, then <hi>Rome</hi> bodies, Common-wealthes.
<hi>Caligula</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a ſlaughter, licked off the blood of the edge of his ſword, as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it had beene a Cordial, and indeed to <hi>Caligula</hi> it might be; So theſe murther, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> delight in murthering. The Chu ch of <hi>Rom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> was wont to be built vp by preaching, and diſputations, yea, Mart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rd m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, but now to exalt their Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarch, they haue found out a more ready, and feate courſe, by poyſons, piſtols, ponyards, m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſacres; <hi>Romes</hi> conver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ors,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19535:19"/> the Ieſuits lively doctrine, or deadly; their operatiue ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, or rather occiſory; they are waxen peremptory in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, (ye know the ſignification of the wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, or if ye doe not, there needes no Comment to explaine it, but their practiſe) they fetch blood at pleaſure, by their new kind of preaching, they are the onely <hi>Pulpit-men</hi> in the World, that ſtrike to the heart; they can equivocate a State to death, a lethall deuiſe. Well, whether this worke had bin a paſtime, yea or no, judge yee; Gunpowder makes mad paſtime, a paſtime it might haue beene to them, but a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhming it had beene to vs. What one liuing ſoule had there remained of that Honourable Aſſembly gathered together? it had beene the great Funerall of the meeting; in a day, in an houre, a minute, neuer ſo many <hi>Worthies</hi> of our Land (ſince the Land had a name) had breathed out together their laſt gaſpe.<note place="margin">—animus me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iniſſe horret.</note> And for the miſeries intended to the Land in generall, the heart may tremble, and the cheekes looke pale at the thought of them, they are incredible, they had beene vnſufferable; Mee thinkes I ſee how this whole Land had beene turned into a Charnel-houſe, where there ſhould haue bene nothing but dead mens corpſes, and bones to bee found; a ſhambles in euery Citty, a ſlaughter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe in euery Country, that as
<hi>Aſia</hi> was called once the <hi>Graue</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> for their many Nobles that had beene there ſlaine, and buried in the time of thoſe warres, ſo England had bin but the Churchyard of the Proteſtants, yea, and that which any ſober Papiſt that is not drunken with the Ieſuits giddy wine, may tremble at, they had bin mercileſſe to men of their owne profeſſion;<note n="i" place="margin">Lam 4.</note> 
                  <hi>The Dragons will draw out their breaſts to their young ones;</hi> but theſe cared not for the cruſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them. For it was the gracious reſolution of <hi>Father Garnet</hi> (who was their provinciall then in
<hi>England</hi>) that it was no ſinne to deſtroy the innocent with the nocent, the deuill himſelfe neuer vttered ſuch a doctrine, hee would not deſtroy them of his owne Kingdome;
<hi>Belzebub</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore may looſe his place, and <hi>Garnet</hi> become hells
<hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intendent.</hi> The ſimple Lay-<hi>Papiſts</hi> from hence may ſee
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:19535:19"/> how the Ieſuits vphold a R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ligion onely to ſuck meanes out of their c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers, or as for their liues they care not; no, as it was ſaid of <hi>Caligula</hi> that he ſlew<note n="k" place="margin">Senatores &amp; cognatos. <hi>Suet.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Senatours,</hi> and his owne kinſmen, ſo they which were of the blood of their owne profeſſion had ſmarted with the reſt. Yea had they by this plot brought in ſome forraine power here to rule, I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what reſpect Engliſh Papiſts ſhould haue found at their hands; As it was in vaine for <hi>Galba</hi> to cry out<note n="l" place="margin">Quid agitis commilitones? ego veſter ſum, &amp; vos mea, <hi>Sueton.</hi>
                  </note> what ayle yee oh my Fellow-<hi>Soldiers?</hi> I am yours, and yee are mine; So in vaine had it beene for them to ſay, what meane yee our Fellow-profeſſours? wee are limmes of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſo are yee; no they would haue put no diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on betwixt one and other, as<note n="m" place="margin">Hiſt. of the
<hi>Neth.</hi>
                  </note> Duke <hi>D' Alua</hi> ſaid once, his ſword knew no difference betwixt the throat of a Papiſt, and a Proteſtant. A <hi>ſlaughter</hi> indeed not to bee paraleld; I read of many, of <hi>Herod</hi> that ſlew his owne ſonne, of <hi>Diocle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian</hi> that killed
<hi>Aper</hi> his father in law, of <hi>Selymus</hi> that wretch that ſlew his owne Father; of
<hi>Periander</hi> that kild his wife, of <hi>Beſſus</hi> that ſlue his owne Maſter
<hi>Darius,</hi> of <hi>Pyrrhus,</hi> that ſlew his truſty ſeruant and Secretary. But here, Father, ſonne, husband, wife, maſter, ſeruant, ſecretary, the ſtate had gone to it;
<hi>Romes-ſlaughter, a State-ſlaughter;</hi> yea and not onely vs whom they counted Heretickes, but the Dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of their owne boſome brought to perdition; So that of their ſlaying wee need not doubt. No, <hi>Our Aduerſaries ſaid, they ſhall neither know nor ſee till wee come into the midſt of them, and ſlay them.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>And cauſe the worke to ceaſe.</head>
               <p>Next, <hi>And cauſe the worke to ceaſe.</hi> And had not this gone with it? had not Religion beene driven into baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? had not our golden <hi>Candleſticke</hi> beene throwne downe? had not our pillar of truth beene raiſed? had not the wide dore of the Goſpell amongſt vs beene lockt vp? had not the ſongs of the Temple ceaſed? yes, your feete muſt have trode no more vpon the pavements of theſe <hi>Sanctuaries,</hi> nor your eares heard any longer the ſweet
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19535:20"/> charmes of ſalvation, this worke ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ceaſed; And a good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worke no doubt had come in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ead; wee ſhould haue had Maſſes againe, the Maſſes of ignorance and in devotion, for what manner of ſupplications are thoſe that are in an vnknowne tongue? the Prieſt ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> conjure then if he will, for if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e doe but conclude <hi>Per Ieſum Chriſtum Dominum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum,</hi> he ſhall have the peoples <hi>Amen;</hi> Maſſes, therefore mockeries, Maſſes, Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>king, yea fitter for a M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e then f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r Church ſeruice: And wee ſhould haue had Traditions, the third Teſtament of Chriſt Ie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us, the Lip-oracle that Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> would neuer ſuffer to come to writing, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n inſpiration forſooth, and yet not to haue an inſpection; And we ſhould haue had the Breaden-God, Tranſubſtantiation, tranſlation; for Chriſt d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ered
<hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> and now it is tranſlated into a God: <hi>Romes</hi> tra ſlated Sacrament, a God they haue made it, though God know but a breaden God: For ſtrange it is, that Chriſt Ieſus would leaue his ſupernall manſion now to dwell in boxes, and pixes, and wafer-cakes; and that hee which hath incorruptible glory would now come, and rooſt vnder elements, that are apt to foiſt, and m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u d, and bee poiſoned, and eaten of vermi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>; a Brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den god indeed, that ſuffer ſuch deperitions; And wee ſhould haue had <hi>Inuocation</hi> of Saints; Inuocation of Saints? what is it but indignity to Saints? For doe the Saints in h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>auen thinke God ſo mere leſſe now, that hee muſt be me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diated to by them to ſhew mercy? doe theſe men thinke Chriſt not a ſufficient Medi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ou, for why <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lſe doe they fly to others? or doe they thinke theſe as ſufficient as Chriſt, for elſe how dare they call vpon them?<note place="margin">Rom. 10.</note> How ſhall they call vpon them in whom they haue not beleeued? Beſid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s it would doe a man good to thinke of their Inuocation of Saints, when
<hi>Longeſſe</hi> that thruſt the ſpeare into the ſides of Chriſt, and S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.
<hi>Chappelet</hi> a notorious vſurer and cheater, and many others that were monſters both in life and death, are put into the n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mber of <hi>Saints.</hi> B ſides we ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> d haue had <hi>Holy water,</hi> fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e water I ſhould haue ſaid; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> why <hi>Holy water?</hi> becauſe it can driu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> away Deuils? ſtrange it is,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:19535:20"/> that thoſe Deuils, that can ſcarce bee driuen away by all kind of watchfulneſſe, prayers, teares, vowes, that they ſhould bee driuen away with the ſprinkling of a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ew drops of <hi>Holy water; Rome</hi> hath an excellent fountaine: what ſhould I ſpeake of their Indulgences, Purgatory, Cruci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>x<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and the like? yet this was the Dagon they fought for, to aduance ſuperſtition againe, to bring in thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Worke,</hi> and to <hi>cauſe our worke to ceaſe. Our Aduerſaries ſaid, they ſhall nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th r know nor ſee till wee come into the midſt of them, and ſlay them, and cauſe the worke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o ceaſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus beloued at laſt haue I ſhewne you the ſwart face of this deteſtable treaſon, the
<hi>Monſter</hi> of all cunning in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions, and cruell conſpiracies: yea<note n="n" place="margin">Quae inferna tantum ſcelus vomuerunt, <hi>Amb.</hi>
                  </note> what mouth of hell euer vomited <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut ſuch a miſchiefe? What now remaines? but that wee ſhould firſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mmemorate: And our beſt commemoration is to make application to God; to acknowledge, admire, magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie this worke. For whom ſhould wee magnifie if not God? And for what ſhould wee magnifie God if not for this? <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt whom ſhould wee magnifie if not God? This great deliuerance was<note n="o" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Homer. Odyſſ.
<hi>1.</hi> Eurymachus ad Telema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cham.</note> 
                  <hi>in the knees of God,</hi> as the Poets phraſe is. <hi>In the knees of God,</hi> and not in the braines of men; <hi>In the knees of God,</hi> and not in the armes of men. For it was nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our fore-ſight, nor force that could haue deliuered vs; 1. not our fore-ſight, for all the ſtate-policy in the world could not h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue helped vs. 2. Not our force, for all our bands of armed ſouldiers could not haue reſcued vs,<note n="p" place="margin">K <hi>Iames</hi> in his ſpeech to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> as that King prudently and piouſly confeſſed; if the Lord had not put into the heart of that noble Lord
<hi>Mount-eagle</hi> to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate the Letter, and into the heart of the King to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret the abſtruſe intricate meaning of the Letter, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to all Grammaticall ſenſe, it had beene impoſſible for vs to have beene delivered; therefore<note n="q" place="margin">Pſal.
64.9.</note> 
                  <hi>All men ſhall ſee, and ſay, this is the Lords doing, for they ſhall perceiue that it is his worke;</hi> therefore <hi>Non nobis Domine, non nobis, Not vnto vs (oh Lord) not vnto vs; not vnto our wiſedome, or valour; Sed nomini tuo, Vnto thy name, thy might and mercy let all
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:19535:21"/> the praiſe be given.</hi> And praiſe let it be.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> For, for what wil we magnifie God if not for this?<note n="r" place="margin">Quiſquis non videt coe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us eſt, quiſquis videt &amp; non laudat. ingratus eſt.
<hi>Aug lib. 1. de civit Dei c. 1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever doth not ſee this to be Gods work, is blind, whoſoever ſeeth it, and doth not magnifie him for it, is vnthankfull.</hi> Oh that there ſhould be faint ecchoes of our praiſes in Gods Courts as this day, that the roofes of Gods Temples ſhould not ſhake with our gratulatory ſounds; Oh bring forth the Lute, and the Harpe, the well-tuned Cymballs, and the loude-ſounding Cymballs, praiſe God in the higheſt for this higheſt favour, which is the moſt matchleſſe tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall deliverance, that ever the finger of God wrought vpon earth: the people of <hi>Rome</hi> had ſo good hopes of
<hi>Caligula</hi> at the firſt, that that day wherein he beg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n his Reign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> (by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of Senate) was called<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                     <hi>Palilia.</hi> Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t.</note> 
                  <hi>The Day wherein Rome was new built:</hi> So we may c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll this day as the day wherein <hi>England was new borne.</hi> And ſhall wee not honour our Birth-day? thay day wherein God hath granted breath, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ife to ſtate, and <hi>Church?</hi> yes, conſider the ſtreames of that River, that ſtill make glad the Citie of the Lord amongſt vs, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the Fountaine from whence they fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w, for, for what will we magnifie God if not for this bleſſing?</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> To deteſt the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome;</hi> for how damnable is that Religion, that hath beene the foſterer and producer of ſuch a devilliſh deſigne? Oh let vs abhorre that Church where Murtherers and Traytors are tolerated, yea Canonized, theſe are<note n="t" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lores non pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nè fructuum ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> pinarum. <hi>Aug.</hi>
                  </note> fruits not of figge-trees, but of brambles; Oh that ever Treaſon ſhould be ſo deepely rooted in the Popes heart, that hee ſhould not bee aſhamed in the ſight of the whole world, to mingle the blood of <hi>Garne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> with the blood of <hi>Chriſt. Oh Holy Father! Oh pure Religion!</hi> Well, let theſe practiſes ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>crab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, horrid, make vs tremble at their religion, and with conſtancie cleave to our owne religion; Yea, ſeeing God ſo miraculouſly, as this day defended our c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſe, let vs neither he doubtfull to embrace this faith, nor baſhfull to profeſſe it.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> To live like a hallowed and conſecrated people vnto God; for, oh that God ſhould be diſhonored h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re, where he
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:19535:21"/> hath opened his boſome, ſpread out his wings, revealed his arme! that his mercies ſhould be freſh before our eyes, and our ſinnes ſtinke vpon earth, cry to heaven? Oh ſacrifice your ſinnes before God, that this day did not deliver you over as a ſacrifice to the rage of your <hi>Adverſaries;</hi> vowe your ſelves to his ſervice, that kept you from them that had vowed your <hi>ſlaughter;</hi> let not your devotions ceaſe, ſeeing <hi>the worke does not ceaſe;</hi> ſeeke Gods face, that hee may ever ſeeke your bliſſe, keepe you from outward invaſion, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward conſpiracy; protect your bodies, preſerve your ſoules, deliver you from the malice of men, and the fury of Devils, give you the happineſſe of a Church viſible vpon earth, and the glory of a Church triumphant in heaven. Which that he may do, God graunt for his mercies ſake. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
